<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The poore-mans preacher A sermon preached at S. Maries Spittle in London, on Tuesday in Easter weeke, being April. 7. 1607. By Ro. Wakeman Bachelar of Diuinitie, and fellow of Ballioll College in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Wakeman, Robert, 1575 or 6-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24951</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101713</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837521</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837521</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1847</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14645)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1847)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1399:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poore-mans preacher A sermon preached at S. Maries Spittle in London, on Tuesday in Easter weeke, being April. 7. 1607. By Ro. Wakeman Bachelar of Diuinitie, and fellow of Ballioll College in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Wakeman, Robert, 1575 or 6-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 90, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Hatfield for Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Ann. Dom. 1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First four words of title within cartouche.</note>
                  <note>Title page marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1847:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1847:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Poore-mans Preacher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>S. Maries</hi> Spittle in LONDON, on Tueſday in Eaſter weeke, being April. 7. 1607.</p>
            <p>By RO. WAKEMAN Bachelar of Diuinitie, and fellow of <hi>Ballioll</hi> College in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prou. 28.27.</hi>
               </bibl> He that giueth vnto the poore ſhall neuer lacke.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matt. 10.42.</hi>
               </bibl> Whoſoeuer giueth to one of theſe little ones to drinke a cup of cold water only, ſhall not loſe his reward.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A. Hatfield</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bill, Ann. Dom.</hi> 1607.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1847:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1847:2"/>
            <head>THE POORE MANS Preacher.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES. 11.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters, for after many dayes thou ſhalt finde it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Salomon</hi> the mirrour of Wiſedome and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (right honorable &amp;c.) had taken a full view of all earthly things, hée found by his owne experience, that there was nothing vnder the Sunne either woorthie of mans impetuous pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, or able to effect mans true felicitie. Hée made himſelfe many great works, he built many goodly houſes, he planted many pleaſant vineyards, orchards, and gardens, and trées therein of all fruit: he had ſeruants and maidens, béeues and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1847:3"/> ſhéepe, ſiluer and gold aboue all that were before him in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> He prouided him his men-ſingers and his women-ſingers, and all the delights of the ſonnes of men. Whatſoeuer his eies deſired he with-held it not from them, neither did he withdraw his heart from any ioy, and yet ſée his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at the laſt of all theſe things, <hi>Vanitas vanitatum vanitas vanitatum, &amp; omnia va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas.</hi> Vanitie of vanities, vanitie of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and al is vanitie: which leſſon, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a good Preacher, hée had abundantly taught the faithfull in the precedent chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this booke, in this verſe now read vnto you, he ſets vp another marke wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at they are to aime, he ſhewes them ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther path that they muſt tread, he chalkes out another race for them to run, and he giues them another precept for them to practiſe. <hi>Caſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thy bread vpon the waters, for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if he had thus ſaid vnto them. O yée ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> why doe you beat your braines and buſie your heads in ſéeking after the vaine and tranſitorie things of this world? why doe you place your
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1847:3"/> chiefeſt happineſſe and delight in ſtrength or beautie, or pleaſure, or wiſedome, or knowledge, or honour, or pompe, or wealth? Where is the ſtrength that ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath not weakened? where is the beauty that age hath not withered? where is the pleaſure that paine hath not purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? where is the wiſedome that folly hath not tainted? where is the knowledge that ignorance hath not blemiſhed? where is the honour that care hath not accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? where is the pompe that time hath not ruinated? where is all the wealth and glorie of this world, that troubles haue not followed? what is the fruit of all theſe things? <hi>Poſſeſſa onerant, amata in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinant, amiſſa cruciant.</hi> In poſſeſſing them they burden you, in louing them they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file you, in looſing them they torment you: this is not a courſe to come to happineſſe, this is not the way to attaine heauen. <hi>Caſt</hi> away theſe trifles O man, leſt they caſt thée away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy God: rather be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to thy poore brother, that God may be mercifull vnto thée. Giue him chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of thy goods that God may liberally reward thée of his grace. Let <hi>thine owne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1847:4"/> bread</hi> féed him, <hi>thine owne</hi> houſe harbour him, <hi>thine owne</hi> apparell cloath him, and <hi>thine owne</hi> wealth miniſter to his want. Doe this to him that cannot doe it to thée againe, make choice of ſuch as cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the like, <hi>caſt</hi> thine almes vnto ſuch poore, as like <hi>water</hi> paſſe away, and will neuer bring agayne what thou giueſt, yea looſe thy money for thy neighbours ſake. This is a meanes to purchaſe Gods fauour, this is a courſe to make thée bleſſed: for howſoeuer, thou doeſt not preſently taſte the fruit of this charitable deuotion, yet a time ſhall come when thou ſhalt finde this reward, if not of temporal things in this life, yet of an euerlaſting inheritance in the reſurrection of the iuſt. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters, for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Few words I confeſſe, beloued, yet the ſubiect of much matter. For as thoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>Ezechiel</hi> were firſt to the anckles, next to the knées, after to the loines, laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch a riuer as could not be paſſed ouer, <hi>Ezech. 47.</hi> ſo the diuine riuers that flow from this heauenly fountaine to make glad the citie of God howſoeuer at the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1847:4"/> firſt view they may ſéeme but ſhallow to the ſhallow conceit of fleſh and bloud, yet vpon further ſearch they are found to bée moſt profound and plentifull in the ſtreames of holſome doctrine to ſatiſfie the thirſt of our ſinfull ſoules: and as hée ſaid of that famous Hiſtorian, <hi>Verborum numero ſententiarum numerum comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> he ſpake as many ſentences as he did words, or as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaid to <hi>Paulinus</hi> concerning the catholicke examples of <hi>Peter, Iames, Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Iude, <hi>breues eſſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter &amp; longas, breues in verbis, longas in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentijs:</hi>
               </hi> that they were ſhort, and yet they were long, ſhort in reſpect of the number of the words, long in regard of the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of much matter in them contained: So I may as truely ſay the ſame of this text, that it is ſhort, and yet it is long, ſhort in the paucitie of words, long in the plentie of matter, euery word carrying his perfect waight, and euery ſyllable his ſubſtantiall ſenſe, and almoſt euery letter his ſeuerall leſſon. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters, for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For art thou rich and bleſſed with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1847:5"/> much wealth, the firſt word is for thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, thou muſt not gather vnto thée, but <hi>caſt</hi> from thée. <hi>Caſt.</hi> Wilt thou know what to <hi>caſt?</hi> thou muſt <hi>caſt bread,</hi> that is, any thing neceſſary for the reliefe &amp; helpe of the diſtreſſed. <hi>Caſt bread.</hi> Wilt thou heare whoſe <hi>bread,</hi> thou muſt <hi>caſt,</hi> not an others, for that is iniuſtice, but thine owne, for that is true charitie: <hi>caſt thy bread:</hi> wilt thou vnderſtand vpon whom to <hi>caſt thy bread,</hi> vpon thy poore brethren, vpon whom whatſoeuer thou beſtoweſt, thou muſt no more expect from them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, then thou lookeſt for that which thou caſteſt away into the ſea. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters:</hi> Wilt thou ſée a reaſon of all this? the reaſon brings with it a reward, the time when this reward ſhall be receaued <hi>poſt dies multos,</hi> after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie daies <hi>for after many daies,</hi> the reward it ſelfe implied in the laſt words, <hi>thou ſhalt finde it: for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that you ſée héere are many parts and circumſtances to be conſidered: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on if I ſhould particularly inſiſt, each of them might require a longer time then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1847:5"/> is allotted mée for the handling of the whole: but for breuitie ſake, the ſumme and effect of all may be drawne into theſe two heads, and diuided into theſe two branches. Whereof the firſt is a precept of a dutie to be performed, in theſe words: <hi>caſt thy bread vpon the waters:</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is a reaſon grounded vpon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a reward to bée receaued, in the next words, <hi>for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it:</hi> the precept is giuen by way of exhortation to Chriſtian charitie: <hi>caſt thy bread vpon the waters:</hi> the promiſe is made by way of remuneration of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an pietie, <hi>for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it. Caſt thy bread vpon the waters,</hi> therein mans dutie is expreſſed: <hi>for after many daies thou ſhalt find it:</hi> therin Gods mercy is declared. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters:</hi> behold our diſtribution to men of things temporall commanded, <hi>for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it:</hi> behold our retribution from God in things tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and eternall promiſed: the one is the exerciſe of our good works héere on earth, <hi>caſt thy bread vpon the waters:</hi> the other is the crowne of our good works
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1847:6"/> there in heauen, <hi>for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it.</hi> The firſt we muſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe for the time: <hi>caſt thy bread vpon the waters:</hi> the latter we muſt expect in time to come, <hi>for after many daies thou ſhalt finde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the bounds and limits of my intended meditations vpon theſe words. God grant I may ſpeake of them, directed by the ſame ſpirit they were indighted, and that all this great and honorable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly may heare and receaue them to their owne inſtruction and conſolation in Chriſt Ieſus. And ſo by your Chriſtian patience I now come to the handling of the parts as they lie in order.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Prima pars.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAſt thy bread vpon the waters.</hi> By the firſt word <hi>mitte,</hi> or <hi>proijce, <hi>caſt: Salomon</hi>
                  </hi> implies that our charitie muſt not onely be extended to ſuch as are néere at hand, but alſo to thoſe that are farre of, as <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> doth expound it, and that we muſt giue our almes <hi>libenter &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beraliter non per extorſionem &amp; quaſi coacti:</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1847:6"/> willingly and liberally, not conſtrained therunto by extorſion and compulſion, as <hi>Bonauenture</hi> will haue it: both of them ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming at <hi>Dauids</hi> admonition, If riches increaſe ſet not your harts vpon them, <hi>Pſal. 62.10.</hi> we muſt not ſet our hearts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our wealth, but as readily caſt them vpon others, as wée haue gréedily gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them vnto our ſelues, knowing that a righteous man by the Pſalmiſt, and out of him by <hi>S. Paul,</hi> is deſcribed to be not a griping and gréedy gatherer vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but a moſt chéerefull and friendly <hi>caſter</hi> vnto others: <hi>diſperſit, dedit pauperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> he diſperſed and ſcattered abroad, that is, he gaue his almes vnto the poore, <hi>Pſal. 112.9. 2. Cor. 9.9. caſt thy bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy bread:</hi> I am not héere of <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthons</hi> and others opinion, who diuing after too ſpirituall a meaning, do by bread vnderſtand <hi>Panem vitae,</hi> the bread of life, the word of God, which they would haue the Preacher thereof to diſtribute vnto the people: for howſoeuer this interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation may be ſound, and agréeable to the analogie of faith, yet certaine I am (and it is the iudgement of our beſt writers,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1847:7"/> ancient and moderne) that it is not for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and ſutable to the circumſtances of this text, I rather by <hi>bread</hi> vnderſtand with <hi>Carthuſian <hi>Corporalem refectionem,</hi>
                  </hi> corporall refection; with <hi>Lauater, <hi>eleemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynam,</hi>
                  </hi> almes; with <hi>Olympiodorus, <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eleemoſynam,</hi>
                  </hi> euery almes; with <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go Cardinalis, <hi>omne beneficium,</hi>
                  </hi> euery good turne; with <hi>Pellican, <hi>omnem eleemoſynam, &amp; omne beneficium,</hi>
                  </hi> both together; with <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablus</hi> and <hi>Illyricus, <hi>quicquid ad vitam eſt neceſſarium,</hi>
                  </hi> whatſoeuer is neceſſarie to mans life: for ſo <hi>bread</hi> in many places of holy Scripture and (one for all) in the Lords praier by a <hi>ſynecdoche</hi> doth ſignifie all things neceſſarie for the preſeruation and ſuſtentation of the life of man. <hi>Caſt thy bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Panem tuum, <hi>thy bread:</hi> tuum non alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> thine owne, and not anothers: for God will not haue vs robbe one, thereby to relieue another, nor to take away from this man to giue vnto that, he likes not ſuch almes déedes, <hi>Siquidem &amp; hoc rapina eſt,</hi> for this is no better then rapine ſaith <hi>S. Chryſoſt. <hi>conc.</hi> 2. de Lazaro, <hi>ſatius eſt non dare quam alterum ſpoliare:</hi>
                  </hi> and better
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1847:7"/> it were not to giue at all then to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our charitie by vniuſt meanes, ſaith that good father, <hi>de verbis Apoſtoli, ſerm: <hi>21.</hi>
                  </hi> but he that will be truely charitable, muſt remember <hi>S. Pauls</hi> rule, not to giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way an other mans goods, but to labour and worke with his owne hands, that hée may haue to giue (of his owne) to him that néedeth, <hi>Eph. 4.28.</hi> and as <hi>Marie</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the féet of <hi>Ieſus</hi> with her owne haire: ſo muſt euery faithfull Chriſtian couer the féete of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> I meane relieue his poore members, at the leaſt with the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities of his <hi>owne</hi> wealth: <hi>honora do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum de tua ſubſtantia,</hi> honour the Lord of thine <hi>owne</hi> riches, ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>Prou. 3.9.</hi> and the bountifull man is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced bleſſed, and why? becauſe hée giueth of his <hi>owne bread</hi> vnto the poore, <hi>Prou. 22.9. Caſt thy bread. Caſt thy bread vpon the waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon the waters.</hi> By <hi>waters</hi> are héere ment the poore and néedie. But this may ſéeme to ſome a ſtrange thing, that <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> will haue vs <hi>caſt our bread vpon the waters:</hi> for whatſoeuer is <hi>caſt</hi> therein, is vtterly loſt, as the common prouerbe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1847:8"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> doe ſufficiently declare, and will <hi>Salomon</hi> haue vs there to beſtow our almes where there will no benefit come either to them or vs by the ſame? Surely beloued in our Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Salomon</hi> would haue vs giue not looking for any thing againe, and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe there are manie maſterleſſe rogues and ſturdie beggers in the world, to whom whatſoeuer is giuen, it is but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed caſt <hi>into the waters:</hi> for being them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues euill beaſts and ſlow bellies, they waſtfully and wantonly and wickedly ſpend the charitable deuotion of the well diſpoſed, and are nothing bettered in their eſtates: but thoſe are not the onely <hi>waters</hi> whereon <hi>Salomon</hi> would haue vs <hi>caſt our bread,</hi> although I grant euen thoſe alſo as they are men and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, (their maners being corrected, and their perſons reſpected) are not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be excluded from our beneuolence. But who then are theſe <hi>waters</hi> whereon we muſt <hi>caſt our bread?</hi> I anſwer ſtill, the poore and néedie, who may be called <hi>waters</hi> in diuers reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1847:8"/>
                  <hi>1. <hi>Reſpectu multitudinis,</hi>
                  </hi> in reſpect of multitude: for as the Angell in the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> told <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> that the <hi>waters</hi> which he ſaw were people, and multitudes, and nations, and toongs, <hi>Reuel. 17.19.</hi> ſo <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> would vs know, that the <hi>waters</hi> which he héere deſcribeth, are multitudes of nations and people, in number ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, in condition poore, on whom we muſt <hi>caſt</hi> the eies of compaſſion. <hi>Liberalitas hinc in multos commendatur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Illyricus,</hi> liberalitie to many is hence commended vnto vs: <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. <hi>Reſpectu agitationis,</hi>
                  </hi> the poore are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>waters</hi> in reſpect of continuall agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and toſſing: for as the <hi>waters</hi> are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome at reſt, but toſſed hither and thither with winde and weather: ſo the poore and diſtreſſed are neuer at quiet, but alwaies vexed with the aduerſe ſtormes of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and tribulation, <hi>eleemoſyna pauperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus afflictis eſt facienda,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bonauenture,</hi> the poore afflicted are to bée relieued with our almes: <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon theſe troubled waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. <hi>Reſpectu humectationis,</hi>
                  </hi> the poore are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1847:9"/> 
                  <hi>waters</hi> in reſpect of moiſtening: for as the <hi>waters</hi> doe not onely moiſten the adioining ſhores, but ſometimes alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflow the bordering fields: ſo they that are pinched with pouertie, are forced ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times not onely with <hi>Dauid</hi> to water their couch with their teares, but euen the boſome of their friends alſo, wéeping and wailing in remembrance of thoſe manie calamities which haue fallen vpon them: O all yée that paſſe by haue pittie on theſe <hi>waters,</hi> I meane on ſuch as are euen tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into watrie fountaines, <hi>quique prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter caſus aduerſos vbertim lachrymantur,</hi> as <hi>Munſter</hi> expounds it, and by reaſon of their miſerable eſtate doe powre downe a ſea of teares. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon thoſe falt and briniſh waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. <hi>Reſpectu tranſitionis,</hi>
                  </hi> the poore are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>waters,</hi> in reſpect of their paſſing away from one place vnto another: for as it is true of all men, in regard of their dailie paſſage in this courſe of mortalitie, which the woman of <hi>Tekoah</hi> told the king, wée are all as <hi>waters</hi> ſpilt vpon the ground, which cannot bée gathered vp againe, <hi>2. Sam. 14.14.</hi> ſo is it ſpecially true of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1847:9"/> poore, they are, ſhall I ſay, <hi>tanquam aquae diffluentes,</hi> as <hi>waters</hi> ſpilt on the ground, that cannot be gathered; certainly they are <hi>aquae tranſeuntes, <hi>waters</hi>
                  </hi> currant vpon the ground that returne not againe what is <hi>caſt</hi> into them: and to this ſenſe manie reade the words of my text, <hi>mitte panem tuum ſuper tranſeuntes aquas,</hi> and they be theſe <hi>aquae tranſeuntes,</hi> theſe <hi>waters tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> vpon whom we muſt <hi>caſt our bread:</hi> call them if you will Gods pilgrims, <hi>qui de loco ad locum, de villa ad villam, de gente ad gentem tranſeunt,</hi> as <hi>Bonauenture</hi> and <hi>Hugo</hi> deſcribe them, that paſſe from place to place, from towne to towne, from countrey to countrey, to craue our chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table almes. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon theſe running waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then you ſée, my brethren, how wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> vnder this metaphoricall ſpéech, <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters,</hi> doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily inforce this morall precept, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute thy wealth vnto the néedie, giue thine almes vnto the poore: <hi>caſt</hi> and <hi>caſt bread, caſt</hi> and <hi>caſt thy bread, caſt</hi> and <hi>caſt thy bread vpon the waters, caſt</hi> and <hi>caſt</hi> it chéerefully, giue what thy hand is able
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1847:10"/> ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Syrach,</hi> with a chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eie, <hi>Eccleſ. 35.10.</hi> and as euery man wiſheth in his heart, ſo let him giue, not grudgingly, or of neceſſitie, for God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a chéerefull giuer, <hi>2. Cor. 9.7. <hi>alacri animo facias eleemoſynam, ne dum panem triſtis dediſti, reſpondeat tibi Deus, panem &amp; meritum perdidiſti,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Pſal. 42. Caſt</hi> and <hi>caſt</hi> ſpéedilie, delaies in giuing are dangerous, a quicke and a readie hand brings with it a double gift, <hi>quantum morae addidiſti tantum gratiae ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traxiſti,</hi> ſaith ſententious <hi>Seneca,</hi> the more delaies thou haſt vſed in giuing, the leſſe thanks thou art to expect for thy gift. The <hi>Graecians</hi> ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſwifteſt graces are the ſwéeteſt: defer not then the gift of the néedie, <hi>Eccleſ. 4.3.</hi> and ſaie not to thy neighbor, go and come againe, and to morrow I will giue thée, if thou now haue it, <hi>Prou. 3.28. caſt,</hi> and <hi>caſt</hi> abundantlie, <hi>deliberanti conſilium, triſti conſolationem, erranti viam, captiuo redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, nonſano medelam, peregrinanti hoſpitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nudo veſtimentum, eſurienti cibum, ſitienti po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; quod cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt neceſſarium indigenti,</hi> ſaith that good father, <hi>cap. <hi>82.</hi> Enchirid. ad
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1847:10"/> Laurentium:</hi> if thy brother be ſimple and deſtitute of vnderſtanding, affoord him thy counſell, if he be friendleſſe, giue him thy comfort, if he be faultie, ſpare not thy brotherly correction, if he be ignorant, lend him thy inſtruction, if he be in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>caſt</hi> him thy ſiluer to redéeme him, if he be ſicke, <hi>caſt</hi> him thy ſalue to cure him, if he be harbourleſſe, grant him thy houſe to couer him, if he be naked, <hi>caſt</hi> him thy garment to cloth him, if he be hungrie, <hi>caſt</hi> him thy meat to féed him, if hée bée thirſtie, <hi>caſt</hi> him thy drinke to refrſh him, if he be in anie want and neceſſitie, <hi>caſt</hi> him this <hi>bread</hi> in my text, that is, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall be requiſite to preſerue him: in a word, caſt it ſincerely without boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, continually without fainting, chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully without repining, ſpéedily without delaying, wiſely without miſſpending: <hi>caſt</hi> it to the néedie, not to the wealthy, for there is no neceſſity: <hi>caſt</hi> it fréely, not looking for anie thing againe, for that is no charitie, <hi>caſt</hi> according to thy eſtate, not more then thou art able, for that is prodigalitie, <hi>caſt</hi> of thine own, and not of others, for that is wrong &amp; robbery,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1847:11"/> 
                  <hi>caſt</hi> in ſecret, and as <hi>on the waters,</hi> not to be ſéene and praiſed of men, for that is méere hypocriſie. Thus muſt wée mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to the neceſſitie of our brethren, thus muſt we ſupplie our neighbours wants, thus muſt we relieue the poore and diſtreſſed, thus muſt we caſt our bread vpon the waters. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They were the words of our Lord <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> that ſpake as neuer man ſpake, It is a bleſſed thing to giue rather than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, <hi>Act. 20.35.</hi> and they were the words of an other <hi>Ieſus,</hi> euen the ſonne of <hi>Syrach</hi> in his booke, Let not thine hand be ſtretched out to receaue, and ſhut when thou ſhouldeſt giue, <hi>Eccl. 4.31.</hi> for as the ſchoole-men tel vs, <hi>bonum eſt ſui diffuſinum, &amp; amor communicatinus eius quod habet,</hi> true goodneſſe is of diffuſiue &amp; ſpreading nature, and vnfained loue is not for it ſelfe alone, but apt to participate and communicate what it hath vnto others: and the Philoſopher through the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of naturall ſpeculation, could ſée as much, that vertues chiefeſt praiſe was rather, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1847:11"/> in the action of diſtributing to others, than in the paſſion of receiuing from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Shal I ſay with the Poet, <hi>res eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genioſa dare,</hi> nay nather with a good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I may pronounce, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to giue is a thing moſt diuine, ſéeing the liberall giuer commeth néerer in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto God, who receaueth nothing from any, but giueth plentifullie vnto all life and breath, and all things, <hi>Act. 17.25.</hi> Giue therefore O man to others, if thou wilt be truely happie, diſtribute vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, if thou wilt be rightly vertuous, miniſter vnto others, if thou wilt be like thy ſelfe, <hi>caſt</hi> vnto others, that thou maiſt be like vnto thy God.</p>
               <p>A duty, beloued, commanded vnto vs in the Law, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended in the Goſpel, approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by nature it ſelfe, and practiſed by the faithful in al ſuccéeding ages. In the booke of <hi>Exodus</hi> the people were commanded to till the land, to dreſſe their vines and oliue trées for the ſpace of ſixe yéeres, but in the ſeuenth yéere the Lord appointed them to let it reſt and lie ſtill, that the poore of the people might eate, <hi>Exod. 23.11.</hi> and it was the expreſſe will of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1847:12"/> God, that in the time of harueſt, they ſhould leaue the gleanings of their corne, and after their Vintage the remainder of their grapes for the poore, <hi>Leuit. 19.9.10.</hi> Nay the precept of the Lord was generall, <hi>Si fuerit apud te egens quiſpiam, de fratribus tuis:</hi> If anie of thy brethren be poore within the land, thou ſhalt not har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thine heart, nor ſhut thine hand from him: but thou ſhalt open thy hand vnto him, and lend him that which is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for his néed; thou ſhalt giue him, and let it not grieue thine heart to giue him, <hi>Deut. 15.7.8 10.</hi> And for this purpoſe in the ſame chapter, the Lord ſaid, there ſhould euer be ſome poore in the land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they might euer haue occaſion to exerciſe their charitie and beneuolence. This was that doctrine which <hi>Eſay</hi> laid downe vnto the Iewes,, <hi>frange eſurienti panem tuum,</hi> deale thy bread vnto the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, bring the poore that wander into thy houſe, when thou ſéeſt the naked couer him, &amp; hide not thy ſelfe from thine owne fleſh, <hi>Eſ. 58.</hi> O what a forcible argument is this to euerie Chriſtian, to ſtretch out his hands vnto the néedie, conſidering
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1847:12"/> that he who aſketh our almes, be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo baſe, is not a ſtranger vnto vs, but fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone, a poore member with vs, of that myſtical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wherof Chriſt Ieſus is the head: hide not then thy face from thine owne fleſh. This was the duty which <hi>Ezechiel</hi> taught his hearers, for deſcribing a iuſt man, he ſpeaks not of his ſtrength and power, his dignitie and honour, his wealth and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but of giuing his bread vnto the hungrie, and couering the naked with his garment, <hi>Ezek. 18.7.</hi> and he taxeth it as a capitall ſinne in <hi>Sodome,</hi> in that ſhée did not ſtrengthen the hands of the poore and néedie, <hi>Ezech. 16.49.</hi> This was that which <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> preached vnto the people, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he that hath two coats, let him part to him that hath none, and he that hath meate let him doe likewiſe, <hi>Luc. 3.11.</hi> This was that which our Sauiour ſo often preſſed: Giue almes of thoſe things which are within, <hi>Luc. 11.41.</hi> and, Sell that you haue and giue to the poore, <hi>Matth. 19.21.</hi> all which places are parallel to this of <hi>Salomon</hi> in my text, <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:1847:13"/>
               <p>What ſhall I ſay more, but as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh, Aſke the beaſts and they ſhall tell thée, aſke the fowles and they ſhall teach thée, ſpeake to the earth and it ſhall ſhew thée, and to the fiſhes of the ſea, and they ſhall declare this vnto thée: Naie looke O man vpon the heauens aboue, and on thy ſelfe below, and tell me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the creatures of God doe not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort preach this doctrine of <hi>caſting</hi> and diſtributing vnto thée: the heauens <hi>caſt</hi> thée their ſwéet influence, the Sunne his light, the Moone her light, and the ſtarres their light, the clouds <hi>caſt</hi> thée their fatneſſe, the aire her ſwéetneſſe, &amp; the fire his warmneſſe, the ſea <hi>caſts</hi> thee his water to waſh thée, his fiſh to féed thée, and many rare things to delight thée, the earth <hi>caſts</hi> thée her herbes, the herbes <hi>caſt</hi> thée their flowers, the flowers <hi>caſt</hi> thée their ſéedes, and the ſéedes <hi>caſt</hi> thée their increaſe: euerie thing <hi>caſteth</hi> ſomething vnto man, to teach one man to <hi>caſt</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vnto an other: and if all this doth not mooue thée, then looke O man into thy ſelfe, the little world: doth not thy hand <hi>caſt</hi> meat into thy mouth, doth not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1847:13"/> thy mouth conuey it vnto thy ſtomacke, and is it not from thy ſtomacke diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted indifferently to the other parts, and all for the preſeruation of the whole? haue not all the members in the body néed one of another? can the mouth ſay vnto the eie, I haue no néed of thée? or the eie to the hand, I haue no néed of thee? or the hand to the eares, I haue no néed of thée? or the eares to the féete, I haue no néede of thée? or the whole bodie to the heart, I haue no néede of thée? nay, doe not each of theſe members affoord their beſt helpe and furtherance vnto the reſt? to teach vs who are all members of the ſame bodie, by giuing our charitable almes to ſupplie the ſeuerall wants and neceſſities one of an other: and whereas (as one obſerueth) <hi>omnia animantia manus habentia illis terram attingunt praeter hominem,</hi> nature, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the God of nature, hath ſo framed &amp; faſhioned all other creatures, that with their hands, or forelegs which are inſtéed of hands, they touch the ground: man onely carrieth his hands lifted from the earth, to ſhew that he ſhould not imploie them in earthly affaires, but rather in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1847:14"/> of his goods, and diuiding of his ſubſtance, and giuing of his riches vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore, and <hi>caſting of his bread vpon the waters.</hi> Such a <hi>caſter</hi> was holy <hi>Iob:</hi> If I haue reſtrained (ſaith he) the poore of their deſire, or cauſed the eies of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to faile; if I haue eaten my morſels alone, and the fatherleſſe haue not eaten thereof; if I haue ſéene any periſh for want of clothing, or any poore without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering: then let mine arme fall from my ſhoulder, and mine arme be broken from the bone, <hi>Iob. 31.</hi> Such a <hi>caſter</hi> was good <hi>Zacheus,</hi> he was no doubt a very rich man, and yet he gaue no leſſe then the one halfe of his goods vnto the poore, <hi>Luc. 19.8.</hi> Such a <hi>caſter</hi> was faithfull <hi>Cornelius,</hi> who is regiſtred by the ſpirit of God to all poſteritie, for a deuout man, and one that gaue much almes vnto the people, <hi>Act. 10.2.</hi> ſuch <hi>caſters</hi> were thoſe two renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned women, the one in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the other in the new: the one was the widow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> who relieued the prophet of the Lord with all the ſubſtance ſhe had, euen a little meale in a barrell, and a little oile in a cruſe, <hi>1. Reg. 17.12.</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:1847:14"/> the other was that charitable <hi>Dorcas</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles,, who was rich in good works and almes which ſhée did, <hi>Act. 9.36.</hi> Finally, ſuch caſters were thoſe woorthie inſtruments of Gods glorie, men and women of famous memorie, whom the Lord hath raiſed vp in this citie as eſpeciall founders and benefactors in many woorthy works. (Héere report was made according to the cuſtome of the place, of the number of poore children, and ſouldiers, and other impotent people, that this laſt yéere were maintained, cured, &amp; by ſome meanes relieued within the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable citie of <hi>London,</hi> in the Hoſpitals of <hi>Chriſt, S. Bartholmew, S. Thomas,</hi> and <hi>Bridewell,</hi> which amounted in all to <hi>4258.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Theſe are excellent things beloued brethren: ſo that as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the time of her ancient puritie, that her faith was publiſhed thorow the whole world, <hi>Rom. 1.8.</hi> ſo we may pronounce of <hi>London,</hi> for theſe her ſingular déedes of charitie, that her faith, and the fruit of her faith, her many good works, are famous thorow the whole world: neither doe I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1847:15"/> thinke that any one citie hath giuen more woorthy teſtimonies of a true and liuely faith: but among all theſe, I finde one good worke yet wanting, &amp; I wiſh it may be hereafter regiſtred in this bedroule, it is that which heretofore many haue much deſired, and I cannot at this time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale it from you: that whereas this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable citie is aboue all the cities in this land, ſo well furniſhed with the choiceſt men for learning, ſent hither wéekely to ſtand before the moſt ſolemne congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is not ſome place prouided at the charges of this citie, and the well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected therein, for their better entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that they are conſtrained to take their diet and lodging in trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Innes, whereby their expenſes are increaſed, their mindes diſturbed, their meditations diſtracted. I ſpeake not this, beloued, in mine owne behalfe, for bleſſed be God, I néed it not, and I haue no cauſe to complaine héerein, my ſelfe receauing ſo kind entertainment of a priuate friend: but I ſpeake it out of a compaſſionate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards many of my poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and fellow-labourers in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1847:15"/> who hauing but ſmall meanes and maintenance, are by authoritie ſent for from the Vniuerſities, to ſupply, if not ſometimes this, yet many times, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſolemne place. The courſe of their ſtudie is héereby interrupted, their paines increaſed, their bodies wearied, their purſe emptied, and yet their perſon, nay, their calling by many is little reſpected: for as that <hi>Leuite</hi> ſometime ſaid, I goe now to the houſe of the Lord, and yet no man receaueth me to houſe, <hi>Iud. 19.18.</hi> ſo many of our <hi>Leuits</hi> may as truely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe of themſelues, that comming hither, they goe vnto Gods houſe to performe that part of ſeruice due vnto him, and yet there is no man receaueth them to lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, no man entertaineth them in his houſe. <hi>Gaius</hi> was but a priuate man, &amp; yet he was the hoſt not of <hi>S. Paul</hi> onely, but of the whole Church, <hi>Rom. 16.23. Simon</hi> was but a poore Tanner, and yet he lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>S. Peter</hi> many daies, <hi>Act. 9.43. Lydia</hi> was but a purple-ſeller, and yet ſhée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted, nay, euen conſtrained the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to come into her houſe, and to abide there, <hi>Act. 16.15.</hi> and will not <hi>London,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:1847:16"/> ſo rich, and ſo religious through her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inhabitants, be as forward héerein as one man? Will not ſuch a publike citie performe as much as a priuate perſon? will not they whoſe zeale in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>) hath prouoked many, be prouoked by others to this good work? That good <hi>Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namite</hi> ſhall euer be remembred while the world ſtandeth, for her loue to the Lords Prophets. Marke I beſéeh you her ſpéech vnto her huſband, <hi>2. Kings 4.</hi> I know this is a holy man of God that paſſeth by vs continually, let vs make him I pray thée a little chamber with walles, and let vs ſet him there a bed, and a table, and a ſtoole, and a candleſticke, that he may turne in thither when he commeth vnto vs. O that wiſe men would not ſcorne to imitate a weake woman, and that you (right Honorable my <hi>L. Maior,</hi> and the right worſhipfull Aldermen of this citie) would vouchſafe in your méetings, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other your ſerious affaires, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine this conſultation, that as this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly woman of God mooued her huſband, out of his priuate eſtate, ſo you would
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1847:16"/> be as readie to mooue one another, that at the laſt out of the publike charge, there may be prouided for the Lords Prophets, a little chamber and a bed, and a table, and a ſtoole, and a candleſticke; I meane a place ſequeſtred from tumult, and fit for meditation, whereunto they may betake themſelues when they come vnto you. Know you not that he which is taught in the Word, ſhould make him that hath taught him, partaker of all his goods, <hi>Gal. 6.6?</hi> know you not that they which mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter about the holy things, eate of the things of the temple? and they that waite at the altar, are partakers with the altar? who goeth a warfar at any time of his owne coſt? who planteth a vineyard and eateth not of the fruite thereof? or who féedeth a flocke and eateth not of the milke thereof? <hi>1. Cor. 9.</hi> They come to ſowe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you ſpirituall things, and thinke you much they ſhould reape your carnall things? they come to bring you heauenly Manna, and will you not affoord them your earthly mammon? they come to ſaue your ſoules, and will not you prouide for their corporall neceſſities? they come
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1847:17"/> to féed you with the bread of life? and will not you beſtow on them materiall foode? they come to comfort you with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of life, and will not you giue a cup of cold water to refreſh them? they come to bring you to the kingdome of heauen, and will not you prepare for them a pilgrims lodging in an earthly manſion? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>S. Paul</hi> told the <hi>Corinthians, 2. Cor. 8.7.</hi> ſo giue me leaue to vſe the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation: as yée abound in euery good worke, in faith and word and knowledge, and in all diligence, and in your loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, euen ſo ſée that yée abound in this grace alſo. Bleſſed ſhal he be that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth ſuch a buſineſſe: bleſſed, and thrice bleſſed he, that thus <hi>caſteth his bread vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe waters:</hi> ſuch a good worke will be acceptable to Almightie God, comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his Miniſters, and honorable to this renowned citie. Conſider my déere brethren what I haue héerein ſpoken, and the Lord God giue you a right vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all things.</p>
               <p>I might héere take occaſion further to incite you to this and the like holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by the example of many of your
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1847:17"/> forefathers in this citie not yet named, who haue excelled in the works of mercy, and with a liberall hand haue <hi>caſt their bread vpon the waters.</hi> But I will not preſſe this point any further: onely of them thus much I ſay, their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance wil be, as the compoſition of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume that is made by the art of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarie, ſwéet as honie in all mouthes, and as muſicke at a banket of wine. They were the great Amners of the king of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, plentifull in the déeds of piety, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in the fruits of charitie, and full of the bowels of compaſſion toward the née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. They are now dead &amp; reſt from their labours, and their works follow them; though I ſée manie now liuing not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them in their works: for alas my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, how farre are ſome of vs degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their ſteps, how farre are we fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from their religious deuotion? <hi>aetas pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentum peior auis tulit nos nequiores, mox daturos progeniem vitioſiorem.</hi> Well might our forefathers be great giuers, and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful <hi>caſters,</hi> but ſurely now the world gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth woorſe &amp; woorſe. We are fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that iron age wherein charitie, the life
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1847:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Chriſtianitie is waxen colde; and the loue to the poore in manie is abated, if not quite diſtinguiſhed. The Naturall Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian writeth of the Eagle the prince of birds, and of the Lion the king of beaſts, that when they haue ſatiſfied themſelues with their praie, they leaue the remaines vnto the inferior beaſts and birds that are vnprouided: but contrariwiſe he obſerueth of the Vulture, a rauenous bird, and of the Woolfe a deuouring beaſt, both of them of a leſſe noble and generous race, that either they deuour their whole praie, or what they leaue, they craftily hide it from others, and couetouſly reſerue it vnto themſelues: Beloued in our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſoared as Eagles in their thoughts, and were Lion-like, truely noble and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall in all their actions: They conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues with a mediocritie, and as for their ſuperfluities, they were willing to diſtribute them to the relieuing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wants, &amp; ſupplying the neceſſities of the néedie: but many of vs like the Woolfe and Vulture being of more baſe and ignoble ſpirits, kéepe all vnto our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1847:18"/> ſelues, and grudge that poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhould ſo much as féede on the crummes that fall from our table. I ſpeake not this of all (for I know many in theſe latter daies as rich in good works, and it may be more truely ſincere in the dooing of them, than they were in former times, as anon by Gods grace you ſhall heare more at large if time will permit) but I ſpeake this, as condemning the backwardneſſe of too too manie, who indéed by reaſon of this glorious manifeſtation of Chriſts Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, ſhould abound in theſe good works anſwerable to their holy calling.</p>
               <p>And héere I may take iuſt occaſion to reprooue two ſorts of men in our land. For my auditorie being ſomewhat gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, I will not leuell the line of my appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to any one particular place. The firſt are they that ſpend much, but where they ſhould not, and they are fooliſhly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall: the ſecond are they that diſtribute nothing at all to any, and they are miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly couetous, both of them offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this doctrine of king <hi>Salomon,</hi> of rightly <hi>caſting their bread vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Of the firſt ſort are the great ones
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1847:19"/> of this world whom the Lord hath bleſſed with much wealth and many poſſeſſions, but what are the fruits of ſo great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance? the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> will tell you in his ſixt chapter: They ſtretch themſelues vpon their iuorie beddes, they eate the lambes of the flocke, and the calues out of the ſtal, they ſing to the ſound of the violl, and inuent to themſelues inſtruments of muſicke, they drinke their wine in bowles, and anoint themſelues with the chiefe ointments: but no man is ſorie for the affliction of poore <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> O how woonderfull hath the ſpirit of God in this place, not pointed at a farre off, but euen toucht to the quicke, ſhal I ſay the princes of Iſrael, I may truly ſay many of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wantons, and wanton nobles of our age, who ſpend their whole patrimonies vpon their pleaſure &amp; riotous ſenſualitie, neuer remembring the afflictions of the diſtreſſed, neuer regarding the neceſſities of their poore brethren. <hi>S. Hierom</hi> in his <hi>26.</hi> epiſtle, commends <hi>Pammachius</hi> a yoong noble man, for his extraordinarie loue vnto the poore, and cals him in reſpect thereof, <hi>pauperum munerarium,</hi> a liberall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1847:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> rewarder of the poore: and in his <hi>9.</hi> epiſtle he gaue this teſtimonie of <hi>Nibridius,</hi> a man aduanced to great honour, <hi>quicquid &amp; Imperatoris largitio &amp; honoris infulae dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, in vſus pauperum conferebat:</hi> Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he obtained either by the Emperors largeſſe, or by his honors prerogatiue, he ſpent it in charitable vſes, towards the poore: good patterns for all thoſe amongſt vs, whom the Lord hath raiſed to great place and meanes, either in Church or Common-wealth, to put them in minde that they be <hi>pauperum munerarij,</hi> liberall rewarders of the poore, and to <hi>caſt</hi> at the leaſt a part of that vnto the néedie, which his Highneſſe bountie and the honorable places they beare vnder him, hath <hi>caſt</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. But alas my brethren how few of them are of <hi>Nebridius</hi> and <hi>Pammachius</hi> minde, how few that expoſe their talents euen their many talents to ſo good vſes? for if they doe, where are the Colledges they haue founded, where are the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals they haue erected? where are the Schooles they haue builded? where are the poore ſchollers they haue maintained? where are the Orphanes and impotent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1847:20"/> they haue reléeued? where are the naked and deſtitute they haue cloathed? where are the harbourleſſe they haue houſed? where are the ſicke and néedie they haue viſited? No, no, beloued, what they ſhould beſtow on theſe charitable vſes, many of them ſpend it on their pride and brauerie, vpon their looſeneſſe and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galitie, vpon their riot and luxurie, vpon their ſurfetting and gluttonie, vpon their pleaſure and ſenſualitie. And as <hi>Greg.</hi> in his <hi>Paſtorall cau. <hi>3.</hi> part. <hi>1.</hi> cap.</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth of ſuch in his time, <hi>cùm fame crucien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Chriſti pauperes, effuſis largitatibus nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triunt hiſtriones;</hi> inſtéed of <hi>caſting their bread vpon the waters,</hi> and giuing to the poore that are pinched with famine, they waſtfully <hi>caſt</hi> their ſubſtance to paraſites and flatterers, to rymers and ieſters, to players and tumblers, to dicers and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to cutters and hackſters, to roiſters and ſwaggerers: they <hi>caſt</hi> that to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and his miniſters, that they ſhould <hi>caſt</hi> to Chriſt Ieſus and his poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. When their dogges fawne vpon them at their table, they féede them with their daintieſt meat, when the walles of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1847:20"/> their houſes are bare, they cloath them with their richeſt arreſſe, nay their horſes and mules whereon they ride, ſaith <hi>Saint Chryſoſtome,</hi> are furniſhed with ſtately foote clothes, and coſtly trappings, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſſed with the pureſt ſiluer and fineſt gold. Their ſeruants attending them are arraied in the moſt gorgeous apparel that can be prouided: when in the meane ſpace the poore ſeruants of Chriſt Ieſus, members of the ſame bodie, children of the ſame father, their own brethren, their owne fleſh, lie hunger-ſtarued at their gates, and wander vp and downe naked in the ſtréetes, and yet they will take no pitie and compaſſion on them. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in hiſtories, that when <hi>Charles</hi> the Great made warre againſt the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens,</hi> that a prince of the <hi>Saracens</hi> came to intreat with him concerning the matter of a truce to be had betwéene them: this prince féeding at a table néere to the king, did wel obſerue the order of his ſeruice, the gorgeous attire of his ſeruants, and the many diſhes wherwith the table was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, whereon the king and his nobles and his ſeruants did vſually féed. At laſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1847:21"/> he ſaw certaine poore men meanely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled, lying on the ground, and féeding on the reliques of the table: &amp; demanding who they were, the king anſwered, that thoſe poore men were the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God, for whoſe ſake he there daily fedde them. Whereupon the <hi>Saracen</hi> angrily replied: What is this the Chriſtians religion, to make more account of their owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants then of Gods ſeruants, to féed them that néed not with roiall chéere, &amp; to cloath them with coſtly garments; and to ſuffer the poore to lie naked and almoſt famiſhed on the ground? An imputation, beloued, howſoeuer vniuſt in reſpect of religion, yet certainly too true in regard of the want of charity, or at the leaſt of the right vſe of charitie in many of great place in theſe our daies: whoſe prodigall courſe the moſt barbarous <hi>Saracen</hi> may iuſtly condemne, in that they neglect the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie: <hi>Et illis menſam amplam adornant qui magis videntur fame ad digerendum cibum, quàm cibo ad nutriendum corpus indigere:</hi> and prouide dainty fare for them, who rather néede abſtinence to digeſt their meat, than meat to nouriſh their bodies.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1847:21"/> But vnto theſe and all of this qualitie, I ſaie with <hi>Iſod. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de ſummo bono, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt ſcelus, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi> It is a hainous ſinne to put the poore mans meat vpon the rich mans table, and to cloath the rich with the poore mans garment: and with <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> in one of his epiſtles, <hi>pars ſacrilegij eſt rem pauperum dare non pauperibus:</hi> it is no leſſe than ſacriledge to giue any thing vnto the wealthy, that belongeth vnto the néedie: for as <hi>Eliſha</hi> commanded the widow to powre her oile not into full but emptie veſſels, <hi>2. Reg. 4.4.</hi> ſo muſt the faithfull extend their charitable deuotion, not to the rich that are full, but vnto the poore that are emptie in reſpect of worldly meanes: according to that of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; When thou makeſt a dinner or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, call not thy rich neighbours, but the poore, the maimed, the lame and the blind, <hi>Luc. 14.13.</hi> knowing that the moiſt ground néedeth not the raine, nor the ſwelling Ocean the drops of water, nor the thicke forreſt the addition of wood, nor the full belly the feaſt, nor the clothed backe more apparell.</p>
               <p>The <hi>2.</hi> ſort of men that offend againſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1847:22"/> king <hi>Salomons</hi> precept of rightly <hi>caſting their bread vpon the waters,</hi> are all coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and hard-hearted worldlings, whoſe eies neuer giue the poore any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſionate looke, whoſe eares are neuer open to their cry, whoſe hands are neuer ſtretched out to relieue them, whoſe hearts are neuer mooued with compaſſion towards them, whoſe bowels are neuer touched with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny féeling of their iniuries. They are like the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> and <hi>Penuel,</hi> that deny a morſell of bread to poore <hi>Gedeon</hi> and his wearie ſouldiers, <hi>Iudg. 8.</hi> They are like churliſh <hi>Nabal,</hi> who would not affoord ſo much as a bit of bread, or a cup of water, or a morſell of meat to <hi>Dauids</hi> ſeruants, but inſtéed of relieuing their neceſſities, they reuile their perſons and condemne their cauſe. <hi>1. Sam. 25.</hi> They are like <hi>ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> which with facilitie do ſucke and draw in water, but we muſt firſt wring and ſquéeſe them if we will haue any iuice out of them. So theſe couetous cormorants doe eaſily ſucke and draw to themſelues the wealth of the world: but perſwade them once to diſtribute vnto the poore, and then you muſt wring &amp; ſquéeſe them,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1847:22"/> if you will do any good with them, <hi>Et citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us clauu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> e manu Herculis extorqueas, aut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam è pumice haurias, quàm ab illis terun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um elicias,</hi> as one ſpeaketh; Sooner may a man wreſt <hi>Hercules</hi> his club out of his hand, ſooner may a man draw water out of the drie pumice, nay ſooner may a man plucke their very eies out of their heads, then get one penie of ſiluer from them to giue to the poore. Let poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> come to their gates, and the dogs will be more compaſſionate towards him then theſe men. Let a man begge of Iewes and Pagans, Turkes and Infidels, and hée ſhall finde more reliefe from them, then from theſe. <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> a heathen Emperour, thought that day to bée loſt wherein he did not benefit ſome poore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and with money reléeue him from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie: But theſe thinke the day loſt, their mony loſt, nay almoſt their life loſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they <hi>caſt</hi> the leaſt quantitie of their goods vnto their poore brethren. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, I haue great compaſſion euen from my verie bowels, as the word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, on the multitude, becauſe they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1847:23"/> haue now continued with me thrée daies, and haue nothing to eate, <hi>Marc. 8.2.</hi> But theſe are ſo farre from the ſympathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing with their brethren in their want, that they are nothing touched or affected though they want their ordinarie ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance many yéeres; they are cruell, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe, vnnaturall, murderers of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>hoc eſt enim hominem occidere vitae ei ſubſidia denegare,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> vpon the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> for they do as much as in them li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth kill men when they deny them their food &amp; daily ſuſtenance. They are the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt fooles of ten thouſand, ſaith <hi>Bonauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>qui minùs Dei amore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quàm denarios re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant,</hi>
                  </hi> that more eſtéeme their goods than their God, their peny than the poore, their bruit beaſt than their Chriſtian brother.</p>
               <p>We read in the booke of <hi>Kings,</hi> that when there was a great famine in <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Ahab</hi> ſaid to <hi>Obediah,</hi> Gouernour of his houſe, goe vnto the land, vnto all the fountaines of water, and to all the riuers, if ſo be we may find graſſe to ſaue the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and mules aliue, leſt we depriue the land of the beaſts, <hi>1. Reg. 18.5.</hi> Marke I beſéech you beloued, how carefull <hi>Ahab</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:1847:23"/> was for the preſeruation of his horſes and mules in the time of famine: but for the orphanes and widowes, for the poore and afflicted people of the land, he taketh no thought at all. And I would to God there were not too many ſuch <hi>Ahabs</hi> now a daies in the world, <hi>qui canibus &amp; equis pluſquam fratrum neceſſitati proſpiciunt,</hi> as a learned father ſpeaketh of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: That more regard the preſeruation of their beaſts than of their brethren, that take more care for their worldly and tranſitory com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, than for the health and welfare of many Chriſtians, that gape after their gaine like gréedy dogges that neuer haue enough, <hi>Eſ. 56.11.</hi> neuer regarding the burdens of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> neuer remembring the afflictions of poore <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> Such were the bowels of compaſſion in holy <hi>Iob,</hi> that hée made another mans affliction to bée his own, he wept with him that was in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his ſoule was in heauineſſe for the poore, <hi>Iob 30.25.</hi> but they are ſo far from this charitable commiſeration, that when the poore come to craue their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, their onely almes are euill words, their onely charitie is reproch
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1847:24"/> and contumely, inſtead of a morſell of bread and a ſmall péece of ſiluer which they ſhould <hi>caſt,</hi> they <hi>caſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> many termes of diſcouragement, and many titles of diſgrace, and many tokens of their hardned hearts. As <hi>Iobs</hi> friends, thoſe miſerable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forters, railed on him, and accuſed him of impietie, <hi>at nec pannum quidem quo vulnera ſua munda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret ei porrexerunt.</hi> But among all their vncharitable tauntings, none did ſo much as affoord him a cloth to wipe and clenſe his wounds: So doe theſe, ſhall I ſaie friends, nay rather enemies of the poore, miſerable comforters indéed, raile at &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile their diſtreſſed brethren, they ſcorne them as the monſters of men, and the moſt abiect creatures of the earth, but at laſt they reléeue them not, they refreſh them not, they ſend them away with emptie bellies and naked backes, to the weakning of their diſtreſſed bodies, and wounding of their afflicted ſoules.</p>
               <p>Yea but me thinks I heare the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings apologie. If I <hi>caſt my bread vpon theſe waters,</hi> I feare I ſhall my ſelfe want before I die. O but hearken what <hi>Dauid</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:1847:24"/> ſaith, I haue béene yoong, and now am old, yet did I neuer ſée the righteous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, nor his ſéed begging their bread, <hi>Pſal. 37.25. <hi>Non memini me audiſſe aut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe mala morte mortuum qui opera miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae libenter exercuit:</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> in his <hi>Offices:</hi> I neuer remember that I ſaw, or heard of any man, that euer died miſerably, that chéerefully performed the works of mercy. And the Lord for thy comfort hath ſaid, I will neuer faile thée, I will neuer forſake thée. Yea but, I haue children to care for, and how ſhall I then <hi>caſt my bread vpon theſe waters?</hi> O but <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> anſwereth this in his <hi>68. <hi>Hom. ad populum Antiochenum.</hi> Abraham</hi> had children, and yet he went foorth into the waies to receaue ſtrangers to lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: So had the widow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> and yet it hindred not her charitie to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. <hi>Vnum habes filium,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine, <hi>Chriſtum putes alterum; duos habes, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum putes tertium; decem habes, vndecimum Chriſtum facias:</hi>
                  </hi> Haſt thou one ſonne, yet let Chriſt Ieſus be an other: haſt thou two ſonnes, yet let Chriſt Ieſus be the third: haſt thou tenne ſonnes, yet let
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1847:25"/> Chriſt Ieſus be the eleuenth: giue of thy loue a portion of thine inheritance vnto him, who of his mercie hath giuen al vnto thée. And if thou wilt reſpect thy childe, &amp; neglect thy Chriſt, then feare this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Lord, either to leaue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde thée no childe at all, or none to beare thy name, or if thou haue any, peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they will prooue ſuch, as ſhall as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digally ſcatter abroad, as thou haſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly, miſerably, and iniuriouſly ſcraped and gotten together thy tranſitorie pelfe. Yea but though I now hold faſt, yet at my death I purpoſe largely &amp; liberally <hi>to caſt my bread vpon theſe waters.</hi> O but remember what <hi>S. Chryſoſtomes</hi> opinion is of ſuch an one in his <hi>18. <hi>Hom.</hi>
                  </hi> vpon the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> where making mention of a couetous churle that would neuer giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in his life time, onely at his death he was content to leaue ſomething to be diſtributed vnto the poore; hée thus ſpeaketh of him, <hi>Non iam das ex tuis, ſed ex ipſa neceſſitate, morti eſt gratia non tibi:</hi> it was neceſſitie, and not charitie that procured from thée thy almes, a man may thanke death and not thée for this deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1847:25"/> Yea but I haue but a little, and how ſhould I then <hi>caſt my bread vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?</hi> O but remember the widowes mite was but a little, and yet it was commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aboue greater gifts, <hi>Mark. 12.43.</hi> A cup of cold water is but a ſmall thing, and yet it ſhall not be vnrewarded, <hi>Matth. 10.42. <hi>Magnitudo eleemoſynae non ex multitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pecumarum, ſed ex alacritate dantium iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatur,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith <hi>S. Hierome</hi> on the fift chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Amos:</hi> The greatneſſe of our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is not eſtéemed according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of our gifts, but to the alacritie of the giuer. <hi>Mentem deus miſericordem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirit, non pecuniae quantitatem,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> God more reſpects a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull minde, than a maſſe of money. <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat Deus intus bonitatem, vbi non inuenit fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatem,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine:</hi> yea our God crowneth a willing minde, where he finds not abilitie. And therefore if thou haue but a little, be not afraid to giue a little, <hi>Tob. 4.8.</hi> and if thou art not able by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thy eſtate, to giue any thing at all, yet at the leaſt put on the bowels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Coloſ. 3.12.</hi> and ſay with <hi>Peter, <hi>aurum &amp; argentum non
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1847:26"/> habeo,</hi>
                  </hi> Siluer and gold haue I none, but ſuch as I haue I giue vnto thée, <hi>Act. 3.6.</hi> Giue thy beſt counſell and aduice, if thou canſt giue nothing elſe, <hi>Saltem loquere vt verbo iuues qui opere non potes:</hi> giue comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table words if thou canſt not performe charitable déeds. Yea but I ſuſpect him to be a lewd-liuer, &amp; why ſhould I then <hi>caſt my bread vpon ſuch water?</hi> O but cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is not ſuſpitious, <hi>tribuamus non quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes cui ſed quare,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Hierome</hi> in one of his Epiſtles: Giue not, regarding the perſon what he is, but the cauſe why thou giueſt. <hi>Laertius</hi> in his <hi>5. <hi>lib.</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>1. <hi>cap.</hi>
                  </hi> reporteth, that when one reprooued a phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher for giuing his almes to a vitious perſon, he anſwered, <hi>Dedi non homini ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ſed humanae ſorti:</hi> I pitied him as a man, not as an euill man. And ſo muſt thou do, ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine, <hi>Et ſi peccator eſt qui petit, da non tanquam peccatori: quòd homo, opus dei eſt; quòd peccator, opus hominis eſt; da operi Dei, noli operi hominis.</hi>
                  </hi> If a notorious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner craue thine almes, giue him as hée is the worke of God, a man indued with a reaſonable ſoule, and made after the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude and likeneſſe of God; not as he is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1847:26"/> the worke of man, a moſt wicked and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full creature. And ſo was it with him in <hi>Gregory, <hi>non quia peccator, ſed quia homo:</hi>
                  </hi> I gaue him my beneuolence, not becauſe I ſuſpected him to be a ſinner, but becauſe I knew him to be a man, one of mine owne nature and condition; <hi>humanum eſt huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis caſibus ingemiſcere:</hi> and if thou wilt not giue him for the loue thou beareſt to man, yet giue him for the loue thou oweſt to God. Such was the loue of <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan,</hi> that he ſaid to his ſonne <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth,</hi> euen halting &amp; lame <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> Feare not, for thou ſhalt eate meat at my table continually, &amp; I will ſhew thée kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for <hi>Ionathan</hi> thy fathers ſake, <hi>2. Sam. 9.7.</hi> So ſuch ſhould our loue be to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, that we ſhould not ſcorne to féed his poore members at our table, &amp; to ſhew them all the kindneſſe we may: if not for their owne ſake, yet for the Lords ſake their and our heauenly father, euer think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on that of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> Whoſoeuer hath this worlds good, and ſéeth his brother haue néed, and ſhutteth vp his compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the loue of God in him? <hi>1. Ioh. 3.17.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:1847:27"/>
               <p>Wherefore O man, if either the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the néedie may conſtraine thée, or the bowels of charitie perſwade thée, or the ſhame of the world inforce thée, or the rules of humanitie allure thée, or the feare of thy God compell thée, or the loue of thy brother intreat thée, giue at the laſt thine almes vnto the poore, <hi>caſt thy bread vpon the waters.</hi> Remember that feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſentence of this wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> in an other booke; Hée that ſtoppeth his eare at the crying of the poore, he ſhall one day crie and not be heard, <hi>Prou. 21.13.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ſaying of a learned Father, <hi>Fruſtra manus ad Deum expandit qui has ad pauperes non extendit:</hi> In vaine he ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out his hands in praier vnto God, that doth not exerciſe his hands in pitie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore. Remember that thou art Gods miniſter, as <hi>Origen</hi> ſpeaketh, to diſtribute a portion to thy fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Do not then like <hi>Iudas</hi> in carrying of the bagge couſen the poore; do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate that to thy ſelfe, that belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to others: <hi>tua non ſunt tua:</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Hierome</hi> in his <hi>8.</hi> epiſtle <hi>ad Demetriadem:</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:1847:27"/> thoſe goods which thou calleſt thine, are none of thine: It is the bread of the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie which thou doeſt detaine, it is the coate of the naked which thou lockeſt in thy wardrope; the ſhooes of the barefoote which lie drying in thy houſe, and the gold that ſhould relieue the poore, that lies cankering in thy coffers, as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. Laſtly remember this and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber all, it is the ſaying of <hi>Gregorie</hi> in one of his <hi>Hom.</hi> and woorthy to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred of euery faithfull Chriſtian: <hi>Quod iacenti in terra porrigitis, ſedenti in coelo da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> What thou giueſt vnto the poore ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the ground, thou giueſt to Chriſt Ieſus ſitting in heauen: What the poore beggeth of thée, Chriſt beggeth of thée, it is Chriſt that aſketh thy houſe to lodge him; it is Chriſt that craueth thy garment to couer him; it is Chriſt that deſireth thy bread to féed him; it is Chriſt that intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thy drinke to refreſh him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as Chriſt ſaid to the woman of <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria;</hi> If thou kneweſt who it is that ſaith, vnto thée giue me drinke, thou wouldeſt haue aſked of him, and he would haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to thée the water of life, <hi>Ioh. 4.10.</hi> So
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1847:28"/> diddeſt thou conſider that when the poore craueth, it is Chriſt that craueth thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable beneuolence, and when thou <hi>caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy bread vpon the waters,</hi> thou <hi>caſteſt</hi> it vpon Chriſt Ieſus, thou wouldeſt not onely giue vnto him of thy tranſitorie treaſure, but intreat of him a greater almes, euen the water of euerlaſting life, and <hi>after many daies thou ſhouldeſt be ſure to finde it.</hi> And ſo I come to my ſecond generall part, to wit, the reward héere propoſed, noted in the laſt words; <hi>For after many daies thou ſhalt finde it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Pars ſecunda.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOr after many daies thou ſhalt find it.]</hi> Although it might ſéeme ſufficient which the holy Ghoſt by king <hi>Salomon</hi> had ſet downe in the firſt words of my text, to perſwade vs to a Chrſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration of the poore, for the will of a maſter is a ſufficient reaſon vnto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and the good pleaſure of a king vnto his ſubiects, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he ſpake the word, gaue ſufficient credit to the ſcholers of that Philoſopher to beléeue
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1847:28"/> the trueth, and follow the preſcription of his precepts: yet the bleſſed ſpirit of God conſidering the dulneſſe of fleſh and bloud in any thing that might concerne their inſtruction in the way of godlineſſe, and well waying how the nature of man is euer ſtirred vp by rewards, the rather to allure vs to this holie dutie, propoſeth the promiſe of a reward to be receaued vpon the performance of this precept: <hi>For after many daies thou ſhalt find it.</hi> Wherein he frameth this argument, <hi>ab vtili,</hi> a moſt forcible argument of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fleſh and bloud: Thinke not much to <hi>caſt your bread vpon the water;</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute your almes vnto the poore, yea to loſe your money for your neighbours ſake, for by this loſſe commeth great gaine, for this, <hi>after many daies you ſhall find</hi> many temporal bleſſings in this life, and eternall glorie in the life to come: for ſo the whole current of Interpreters ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound theſe laſt words of my text. And héere my brethren as the carkaſe of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſah</hi> lying in the midſt of the way cauſed the people to ſtand ſtill, <hi>2. Sam. 20.12.</hi> So me thinkes in the verie entrance of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1847:29"/> this ſecond part, there ariſeth a ſcruple to ſtaie my paſſage, and hinder my courſe, which when we ſhal remooue, we may the better procéed and goe forward in the ſame. For whereas the ſpirit of God by <hi>Salomon</hi> doth héere <hi>implicitè</hi> ſet downe a temporall and eternall reward to all them that are plentifull in their charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble déeds towards the poore: heereupon the aduerſaries of the trueth miſinterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the place, doe preſently conclude, that theſe works of mercie did merit and deſerue this reward at the hand of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God. The vanity of which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, ſhall God willing plainly appéere vnto you, if you will vouchſafe héerein a little to affoord mée your Chriſtian pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and accuſtomed attention. And if there be any héere preſent, that haue béene ſeduced to fauour the doctrine of popiſh merits, and are not yet fully ſatiſfied and ſetled in the trueth, let mée deſire them in the bowels of Chriſt Ieſus (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they will obſtinately continue in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) to laie aſide all preiudicate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, either of my perſon or of this cauſe, and with indifferent eares to heare,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1847:29"/> how in this one point, by the diſciples of Antichriſt, our Church hath béene wronged, theſe weake ones abuſed, the Scriptures peruerted, and the faithfull generally ſcandalized. <hi>For after manie daies they ſhall find it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A temporall and eternall reward, ſaie they, is héere promiſed to him that <hi>caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his bread vpon the waters,</hi> that giueth his almes vnto the poore, <hi>ergo</hi> this cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable almes merited this reward. And the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> in their annotations vpon <hi>Rom. 2. ſect. 2.</hi> affirme that Chriſtians good works are meritorious, and the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſaluation: and vpon <hi>1. Cor. 3. ſect. 2.</hi> men by their good works deſerue heauen: &amp; <hi>Bellarmine</hi> their great champion in his <hi>4. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. de bonis operibus,</hi>
                  </hi> is of opinion, that good works, and namely almes déeds, (whereof <hi>Salomon</hi> héere eſpecially ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) doe merit eternall life, not onely <hi>ex congruo,</hi> by a kinde of congruitie, which ſome of the Schoolemen allow, but alſo <hi>ex co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>digno,</hi> of condignitie, or worthines in the higheſt degrée, which many of the ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doe denie. The reaſon of this their aſſertion they fetch from that place, <hi>Luc.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1847:30"/> 10.7.</hi> The labourer is woorthy of his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; but the faithful are laborers, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life is their wages promiſed, <hi>Matth. 20.8. <hi>ergo</hi>
                  </hi> the faithfull are woorthy of, &amp; by their works doe merit eternall life. But marke, I beſéech you brethren, how like the ancient heretikes, our <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> by their curſed gloſſes corrupt this Scripture, and violently wreſt it from its true meaning: for whereas our Sauiour there ſaieth; The labourer is woorthy of his hire, he doth not by hire or wages vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the kingdome of heauen or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, but rather a temporall reward, as the circumſtances of the text do manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare it. For Chriſt Ieſus there ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his diſciples to preach the Goſpell, biddes them carrie no bagge nor ſcrip, nor ſhooes with them: but into what houſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they did enter, they ſhould tarrie there, eating and drinking ſuch things as were ſet before them: for the labourer, ſaith he, is woorthie of his hire. His mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning there is nothing elſe but as <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>1. Corint. 9.</hi> that his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples preaching the Goſpell, ſhould liue of the Goſpell, and ſowing ſpirituall
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1847:30"/> things vnto the people, ſhould be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with their corporall reliefe. Againe, ſuppoſe that wages or hire did ſignifie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, as out of <hi>Matt. 20.</hi> they prooue, yet ſhall we thinke by our good déeds to demerit the ſame? ſéeing in that very chap. you ſhall finde, that they who were called at the laſt houre, had as large a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as they that came at the firſt: which had neuer béene if merit had béene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected: and therefore as <hi>Saint Ambroſe</hi> ſaith in his <hi>lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> de vocat. gentium: Cùm hi qui in multo labore ſudarunt,</hi> ſéeing they which were in all the labour recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no more than the laſt, <hi>intelligant do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſe gratiae, non operum accepiſſe merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem:</hi> let them vnderſtand they receaued a gift of Gods grace, and had nothing in them to merit this reward of their works.</p>
               <p>Yea but in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> the words are more plaine, and the ſpirit there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth them woorthy, <hi>Reuel. 3.4.</hi> Thou haſt a few names yet in <hi>Sardi,</hi> which haue not defiled their garments, and they ſhall walke with me in white for they are woorthie. But how beloued? <hi>non</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſed</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they are not abſolutely woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1847:31"/> but reſpectiuely in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of thoſe wicked ones in <hi>Sardi,</hi> that had conſented to idolaters, and polluted their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with euill, and were altogether pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane. So doth <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> expound it writing on the <hi>2. Timoth. 1. <hi>quantum ad caeterorum comparationem digni ſunt, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad rem ipſam omnes indigni:</hi>
                  </hi> in reſpect of others they are woorthy, but in regard of the thing it ſelfe, they are all vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie. Or elſe they are woorthy not ſimply of themſelues, but becauſe God did ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Non ex operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſed pura gratia:</hi> as a good writer will haue it: Not by the merit of their works, but by the imputation of Chriſts woorthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not becauſe they are clenſed by their almes, but becauſe their robes are made white in the bloud of the Lambe, <hi>Reuel. 7.14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea but that place, <hi>Matth. 24.</hi> cannot be anſwered: Receaue the kingdome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you from the beginning of the world, for I was hungrie and yée fed me, naked and yée clothed me, &amp;c. <hi>ergo,</hi> almes déedes are the efficient cauſes of euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, &amp; the <hi>caſting our bread vpon the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1847:31"/> waters,</hi> ſhall merit heauen for vs. Indéed my brethren this is the Scripture they moſt preſſe: but if you will a little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this place with me, I doubt not, but as that <hi>Aegyptian</hi> was ſlaine with a ſpeare taken out of his owne hands, <hi>2. Sam. 23.21.</hi> So our aduerſaries ſhall bée confuted out of theſe words, which they alledge for the defence of their own cauſe. For if we looke into the text, we ſhall find that this kindgome was prepared for them from the beginning of the world. Whence wée may frame againſt them this argument: If this kingdome were prouided for the faithfull before they had done any almes déedes at all, then did not the faithfull by their almes déedes as by precedent cauſes merit or deſerue the ſame: But this kingdome was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for the faithfull before they had done any almes déeds at all, euen before the foundation of the world was laid: <hi>ergo,</hi> the faithfull did not by their almes déed merit or deſerue the ſame.</p>
               <p>Againe, our works are ſaid to be meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, when we doe them of our owne frée will and pleaſure, and not of due debt,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1847:32"/> for when wée doe that which wée are bound to doe, we doe no more but our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. But behold, beloued, and conſider what the Apoſtle ſaith, We are his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, created in Chriſt Ieſus, to good workes, which God hath ordained wée ſhould walke in them, <hi>Eph. 2.10.</hi> and the particular good works of almes déedes are in my text and in many other places of holy ſcripture required of vs. We are not left to our owne frée will and pleaſure whether we will doe them or no, but as <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelfe concerning the preaching of the Goſpell, Neceſſitie is laid vpon me, and woe be vnto me if I preach not the Goſpell, <hi>1. Cor. 9.18.</hi> So may all Chriſtians ſay of themſelues in this behalfe, there is a neceſſitie laid vpon vs to relieue the poore, to <hi>caſt our bread vpon the waters,</hi> and woe be vnto vs if we doe it not. And ſhall we then make our almes meritorious, when neceſſitie requireth that at our hand? Did the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter thanke his ſeruant becauſe he did that which was commanded him? <hi>Luc. 17.9.</hi> and doe we thinke that when wée haue done all that is commanded vs, wée
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1847:32"/> ſhall be in any better ranke then vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruants? or doe we looke the Lord ſhould thanke vs, or that he ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow the kingdome of heauen on vs for the woorthineſſe thereof?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, betwéene the worke and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward there ſhould be an equall proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, otherwiſe it cannot be ſaid to merit: for if the reward be more than the works, it is not a reward of deſert, but a gift of good will. Whence it is manifeſt, that our beſt almes can neuer merit this kingdome of heauen, becauſe none of them can equal it. What is a cup of cold water to eternall life? what is a morſell of bread to a crown of glory? what is a ſmall mite to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen? Nay what are our beſt works to ſuch an immortall reward? All the afflictions of this life are not woorthie of that glory that ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs, <hi>Rom. 8.18. <hi>Quid poſſumus dignum facere praemijs coeleſtibus,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> in his <hi>20. <hi>ſerm.</hi> in Pſal. 119.</hi> what can we doe to deſerue heauen? <hi>Beatae vitae nullus poteſt aquari labor, nulla operatio, paſſiones nullae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> in <hi>Pſal. 142.</hi> to bleſſed life no labour, worke, or ſuffering can bée
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1847:33"/> equall, <hi>Quid ſunt merita noſtra ad tantum gloriam?</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Bernard</hi> in his <hi>1. <hi>ſerm. De Annuntiatione.</hi>
                  </hi> What are all our merits, euen our beſt merits in compariſon of ſo great glorie? To theſe I might adde the teſtimonies of <hi>S. Chryſoſtome, S. Baſil, S. Hierome, S. Auguſtine,</hi> and the reſt of the antient fathers of the Church, who in many places of their works (being rightly vnderſtood) doe beat downe this monſter of popiſh merits, to the ſhame of our fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrimen, who are not aſhamed to publiſh to the world, that all the Fathers, Councels, Reaſons, Scriptures, are in this point for them, &amp; againſt vs. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you ſée the contrary hath béene in part, and might be in the whole prooued, if time would permit. And the word of God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſo oppoſite vnto them, that I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell not if that godly martyr was ſo tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly perſwaded of this trueth, that hée ſaid vnto his enimies: He that can ſhew me in any Scripture that our almes déeds or beſt works doe merit heauen; for the firſt Scripture, I will without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudgement loſe both mine eares, for the ſecond my toong, for the third my
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1847:33"/> necke, as in our Acts and Monuments it is reported of him.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſée (right Honorable, &amp;c.) the <hi>Babel</hi> of ſelfe iuſtifying merits, whereby our aduerſaries perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues they aſcend vp into the higheſt heauens, is at the laſt fallen downe, becauſe it is built vpon the ſands of mans inuention, and not on the true rocke Chriſt Ieſus: <hi>Vbi enim Chriſtus non eſt fundamentum, nullum eſt boni operis aedificium,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorie:</hi> Where Chriſt is not laid as the corner ſtone for a good foundation, there will bée no place to erect the building of good works. I ſpeake not this, nor any thing in this argument, to withdraw men from doing good, or to diſcourage them in their charitable deuotions, as our aduerſaries in their bookes moſt falſly accuſe vs, moſt vncharitablie ſlander vs, and moſt iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly traduce vs. For wée both allow of good works, and preach good works, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call vpon our hearers as true profeſſors to manifeſt their faith by theſe fruits, as this place this day, and many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in this citie almoſt euery day can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently witneſſe. Nay, we confeſſe a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1847:34"/> vſe of good works, by them we ſet foorth Gods glory, <hi>Matt. 5.16.</hi> by them our faith is made knowen for the good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of others, <hi>Iac. 2.18.</hi> by them our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are quieted, and our election daily made ſure vnto vs, <hi>2. Pet. 1.10.</hi> Yea wée attribute ſo much vnto them, that ſome of our Church haue publiſhed whole Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes that good works are neceſſarie vnto ſaluation. What can they ſay more than we doe in the behalfe of good works, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they will forſake the trueth? And yet ſée the malice of theſe men; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding we thus ſpeake, and we thus write; they are not aſhamed to ſay, that our Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is a Goſpell of libertie, epicuriſme, and ſenſualitie; that we haue ſlacked mens charitie, and quenched their deuotion, that we condemne good works as vncleane, ſinfull, and hypocriticall; that we plucke them vp as wéedes by the roots, and caſt them foorth of the doores as children of the bond woman, not woorthie to inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite with the frée borne; that we preach nothing but <hi>ſola fides, ſola fides;</hi> and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as their <hi>bona opera</hi> haue built many good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Colledges and Schooles, and Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1847:34"/> our <hi>ſola fides</hi> hath pluckt them downe againe.</p>
               <p>Beloued in our Lord and Sauiour, to remooue this falſe imputation: what our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of good works is, you haue already heard, what our practiſe in good works is, let the world iudge. Indéed in the time of Poperie the ſéely people were taught, that if they would doe ſuch a good worke they ſhould thereby merit heauen, and God were vniuſt if he did not giue it them. And if they would doe ſuch a good worke, they ſhould receaue pardon not onely for their owne ſinnes, but alſo for the ſinnes of their poſteritie to many generations. No maruell then (being thus deluded by iugling friers) if in thoſe daies they did plentifully <hi>caſt their bread vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> if they did abound in diſtributing to the poore. For what will not a man giue to purchaſe heauen, and to ſaue his owne ſoule? and I confeſſe, that we liue in the dotage of the world, wherein our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath told vs; Charitie ſhall waxe cold, and the hearts of many ſhall be hardned from doing good. Yet for all this I dare vndertake that for this laſt age, and in the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1847:35"/> remembrance of ſome yet liuing ſince the cléere ſunſhine of the Goſpel hath enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Hemiſphere of our Church, there haue bene more Colledges founded, more Hoſpitals erected, more Schooles buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, more poore Schollers maintained, more Orphanes and impotent reléeued, more charitable déedes exerciſed, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in our land, particularly in this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous citie, euer renowned for her good works, I dare be bold to ſay, than in any, I thinke I may truely ſay, than in many ages vnder poperie and ſuperſtition. Yet God forbid we ſhould thinke that they who haue moſt excelled in thoſe holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, did héereby merit heauen: For eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life is the gift of God, <hi>Rom. 6.23.</hi> and yée are iuſtified freely by grace, <hi>Rom. 3.24. <hi>Gratis per Gratiam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gratia autem nullo modo eſt gratia, niſi omni modo ſit gratuita.</hi>
                  </hi> As hée ſpeaketh; And by grace yée are ſaued through faith: not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God: not of works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt. <hi>Epheſ. 2.8.9.</hi> I confeſſe héere in my text is a reward propoſed to our almes déedes, that if we <hi>caſt our bread vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the waters, after manie daies we ſhall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1847:35"/> be ſure to finde it:</hi> but reward is as well of fauour as of debt, <hi>Rom 4.4.</hi> and if God in promiſing this reward be a debter vnto vs, it is but in that ſenſe as <hi>S. Aug</hi> vpon the <hi>83. Pſal.</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Debitorem ipſe ſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus fecit non accipiendo, ſed promittendo: non ei dicitur, redde quod accepiſti, ſed redde quod promiſiſti:</hi> God hath made himſelfe a debtor vnto vs by promiſing, not by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing any thing at our hands to deſerue the ſame. <hi>Quicquid autem promiſit, indignis promiſit, vt non quaſi operibus merces pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteretur, ſed gratia gratis daretur:</hi> as the ſame Father ſpeaketh: And whatſoeuer God hath promiſed, hée promiſed vnto thoſe that were vnworthy, that it ſhould not be promiſed as a reward vnto works, but as grace fréely giuen.</p>
               <p>Wherefore to conclude this point, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord hath promiſed euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reward all them that <hi>caſt their bread vpon the waters,</hi> not for the merit of their worke, but for his owne frée fauour and mercie, <hi>diſcamus de noſtris diffidere me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis:</hi> Let vs hencefoorth learne to diſtruſt our owne merits: <hi>quaerant alij meritum, nos gratiam inuenire ſtudeamus:</hi> Let others,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1847:36"/> (ſuch as all popiſh fauorits are) ſéeke after heauen by theſe meanes; but let vs labor to finde grace, ſaying with <hi>S. Bernard, <hi>Meritum meum miſeratio domini,</hi>
                  </hi> my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is the Lords mercie: and with <hi>S. Auguſtine, <hi>Si miſericordiae domini multae, multus ego in meritis:</hi>
                  </hi> If God be rich in mercy, I ſhall ſurely abound in merits. Thus if wée conceaue humbly of our ſelues, God will eſtéeme highly of vs; &amp; if with a lowly mind, we do good to others for Gods ſake, God will with a liberall hand doe good vnto vs for his mercies ſake: and if we will <hi>caſt our bread vpon the waters,</hi> not thinking of any merit in ſo ſmall a worke, God will <hi>caſt</hi> euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioies vpon our ſoules, not reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our many wants. And ſo paſſing from this controuerſie, I come at laſt to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of the rewards here propoſed: <hi>For after many daies thou ſhalt finde it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherin two things offer themſelues to our conſideration: firſt, the time when this reward ſhall be receaued, in theſe words, <hi>for after many daies.</hi> Secondly, the reward it ſelfe in the laſt words, <hi>thou ſhalt find it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For after many daies.]</hi> Some read the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1847:36"/> words, <hi>in multitudine dierum,</hi> in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of daies thou ſhalt finde it: as if hée ſaid, <hi>Si in pauperes liberalis fueris, deus vitae tuae dies producet:</hi> If thou wilt be liberall towards the poore, God will prolong the daies of thy life. A true interpretation, for I doubt not but God doth many times bleſſe them with long life and many yéeres, that looke vpon his poore members with mercifull and compaſſionate eies.</p>
               <p>Others, and thoſe in number ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and in iudgement moſt authenticall, doe thus read the words; <hi>Poſt dies multos, <hi>after many daies thou ſhalt finde it:</hi>
                  </hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giuing vs to vnderſtand, that howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer God in his wiſedome deferreth the remuneration of our Chriſtian charitie, yet certainly he hath a reward in ſtore for vs, which at the laſt we ſhall aſſuredly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue. And this I take to be the naturall and proper ſenſe of king <hi>Salomon</hi> in this place: <hi>For after many daies thou ſhalt find it.</hi> For whereas in the former part he had vſed a pretie kind of <hi>prolepſis,</hi> or preoccupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which a worldly minded man to this purpoſe might haue vſed: Whatſoeuer I giue vnto the poore is aſſuredly loſt, as if
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1847:37"/> I <hi>caſt my bread into the ſea,</hi> and I ſhall neuer expect a recompence for the ſame: He now anſwereth this doubt, <hi>Et occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hominum impatientiae, qui, niſi è veſtigio compenſationem accipiant, ilico animum abij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt:</hi> as one ſpeaketh, and he héere méet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the impatiencie of thoſe men, who preſently deſpaire, if God reward not their almes out of hand: But <hi>Salomon</hi> héere tels them, that if the Lord hath not yet rewarded them, yet they muſt expect and waite his leaſure, they muſt tarie a day and a day, nay <hi>many daies,</hi> and then at the laſt they ſhall be ſure to receaue it: &amp; if in the meane ſeaſon they liue in want, and take vp the crie of thoſe faithfull ſoules, <hi>Vſquequò domine, vſquequò?</hi> how long Lord, how long ſhall we expect our reward? the ſpirit ſhall teſtifie to their ſpirits, that Chriſt himſelfe doth ſay vnto them; Behold, I come quickly, and my reward is with me, to giue to euery man according vnto his works, <hi>Reuel. 22.12.</hi> For ſo it is, beloued brethren, ſometimes God preſently rewardeth the charitable beneuolence of his children, as hée did the widow of <hi>Sareptah,</hi> who immediately
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1847:37"/> vpon her reléeuing of <hi>Eliah,</hi> had her meale &amp; oile increaſed according to the word of the Lord, <hi>1. Reg. 17.16.</hi> Somtimes <hi>differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur retributio, non deficit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bonaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture:</hi> Well may Chriſt deferre it for a time, but he doth not forget it for euer. It may bée that for thy loue to the poore members of Chriſt, God in his loue to thée wil in time increaſe thy corne, thy wine, thy oile, and thy ſtocke, and then in thy ſelfe and thine owne eſtate <hi>after manie daies thou maieſt find it.</hi> It may be, that thoſe poore children whom thou now feedeſt at thy table, and clotheſt with thy garments, may one day be ſo enabled by Almightie God in their eſtate that they may féed and cloath thy children, when they may bée brought to much want and miſerable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie: and then in thy children, <hi>after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie daies thou maieſt finde it.</hi> The ſumme and effect of all is this: God that is before all time in recompenſing the good works of his children, will not bée tied to this or that circumſtance of time: onely wée may be well aſſured, that one time or an other he will reſtore our liberalitie mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold into our boſome, by giuing vs, <hi>ant
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1847:38"/> quod petimus, aut quod melius eſt, aut quod ſufficit:</hi> either what wée deſire, or that which is better, or that which is ſufficient.</p>
               <p>Learne then, my brethren, a ſimilitude of the huſbandman, he caſteth his ſéed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ground, the corne dieth, the winter commeth, froſt and ſnow and tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous weather falleth thereon, and who would not thinke hée had laboured in vaine? yet the huſbandman patiently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth and tarrieth the time of harueſt, and then he receaueth a plentiful increaſe. So when we giue our almes, what doe we elſe but <hi>caſt,</hi> ſhall I ſay our ſéed, vpon the ground, nay (whereof there may bée leſſe hope) <hi>our bread vpon the waters?</hi> Yet certainly as that, though in mans iudgement caſt away, ſpringeth and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, and beareth much fruite: So this in time ſhall returne vnto a happy har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt. <hi>Si enim non perit ſemen quod in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram proijcis, quid times periturum quod in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini manu reponis?</hi> If the ſéede periſh not which is caſt into the earth, much leſſe ſhall that be loſt that is left in Gods hand, that is laid vp in Chriſts ſtore-houſe, the poore-mans bagge. Learne a ſimilitude
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1847:38"/> of great purchaſers; they giue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times great ſummes of money for reuerſions, which themſelues ſometimes neuer liue to enioy, but their children after them receaue the benefit thereof: ſo let not vs thinke much to diſburſe our ſummes, our manie ſummes, towards the reliefe of our poore brethren, knowing that if the benefit héereof come not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to our ſelues, yet it will come op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely to our poſteritie: <hi>For after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daies we ſhall finde it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea but, will ſome men ſay, how is this true? I haue oftentimes <hi>caſt my bread vpon the waters,</hi> giuen mine almes vnto the poore, and I haue a long time expected this reward, &amp; as yet I can finde nothing. O but hearken what <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth in one of his <hi>Hom.</hi> Examine thy ſelfe O man, hath not God rewarded thy charitie with any bleſſing: who then hath giuen thée thy health, thy wealth, thy food and apparell: or if thou haſt not yet in a full meaſure taſted héereof, expect notwithſtanding, and waite the Lords leiſure, ſurely hée deferreth theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings for thine aduantage, that hée may
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1847:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> pay thée at the laſt with the greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. For God is not like that king in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who would alwaies ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I will giue to all men, and yet for all this, gaue nothing to any man. He is <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen</hi> in all his promiſes, and in time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient he will performe them. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the womans ſéede was inſtantly made and oppoſed as a comfort againſt <hi>Adams</hi> fall, yet it was performed <hi>3900.</hi> yéeres after in Chriſt Ieſus. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of <hi>Iſraels</hi> returne out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> is made a comfort vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet <hi>400.</hi> yéees ſeruitude muſt bée firſt indured, but in time conuenient this promiſe ſhall be performed. The promiſe of the Scepters continuance till <hi>Siloes</hi> comming is made to <hi>Iudah,</hi> yet ſhall many ſtep in of other tribes; <hi>Moſes</hi> out of <hi>Leuies</hi> tribe, <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> out of <hi>Ephraims</hi> tribe, <hi>Saul</hi> out of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamins</hi> tribe; yet in time conuenient a poore <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhall be reſtored to the ſcepter of <hi>Iudah. Ioſeph</hi> was not preſently lifted vp aboue his brethren, but manie bitter gréefes were before indured. <hi>Iudah</hi> did not inſtantly finde releaſe by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> but many ſorowfull ſongs by the waters of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1847:39"/> 
                  <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt be chaunted: but at length the ones dignifying, the others deliuery, were in time conuenient performed. Hée that deferred the promiſed ſéed ſo manie hundred yéeres, and then ſent; <hi>Iſraels</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance ſo many ſcore of yéeres, and then wrought; croſt <hi>Iudahs</hi> and <hi>Ioſephs</hi> hopes ſo many waies, and then granted: why ſhould we doubt but that the ſame God with whom the preſent and future tenſe is all one, will in conuenient time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them that reléeue his? Why ſhould we doubt but that if we thus lay out our money for the Lord, the Lord at the laſt will reſtore it? Why ſhould we doubt, but that if we thus lend vnto the Lord, the Lord at the laſt will repay it? Why ſhould we doubt, but that if we thus <hi>caſt our bread vpon the waters,</hi> the Lord at the laſt will reward it, though we expect it <hi>manie daies?</hi> And ſo from the time héere ſpecified, <hi>after manie daies,</hi> I now come to the reward it ſelfe héere propoſed in the laſt words, <hi>thou ſhalt finde it,</hi> whereof by your patience a word or two, and ſo I will commit you to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt finde it] <hi>inuenies illum,</hi>
                  </hi> that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1847:40"/> is, ſaith <hi>Bonauenture, <hi>retributionem pro illo,</hi>
                  </hi> a recompence for it. And what is this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence? It is, ſaith one, <hi>ſeptuplum, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuplum, millecuplum:</hi> ſeuenfold, an hundred fold, nay, a thouſand fold more than the morſell of <hi>bread we caſt vpon the waters,</hi> more than the meaſure of almes we giue vnto the poore: it is <hi>merces temporalis in hoc ſeculo &amp; aeterna in futuro:</hi> a temporall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of things tranſitorie héere on earth, &amp; a full fruition of things eternall there in heauen: as the <hi>Caldie</hi> paraphraſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther interpreters doe expound it. And here you ſée my brethren what a large field I haue yet to walke in, and what a ſea of matter lies before me: but my purpoſe is not to tread euery path, nor to ſound eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Ocean. I will paſſe ouer this point <hi>tanquam canis in Nilo lambens, vel vt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das in puluere curſitans,</hi> as the dogs vſe to lap in <hi>Nilus,</hi> and as <hi>Ladas</hi> trips it vpon the ſands, catching a little here and there, and ſcarſe leauing the print of my ſpéech any where: commending the reſt to your priuate meditations, and to the effectuall operation of Gods holy ſpirit in your obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient hearts.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:1847:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt find it]</hi> That is both a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall &amp; eternall reward. Firſt thou ſhalt finde a temporall reward. Honour the Lord, ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> by thy riches, that is, in diſtributing them vnto the poore: So ſhall thy barnes be filled with abundance, and thy preſſes ſhall burſt with wine, <hi>Pro. 3.9.10.</hi> For as a fountaine, ſaith <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> the more it is drawne, the more it is filled with freſh, and, for the moſt part, ſwéeter water: So the more we draw the fountaine of our bounty, by <hi>caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> vnto the poore, the more is our ſtore repleniſhed with a new ſupplie of manie bleſſings. And as when <hi>Ieſus</hi> brake and diſtributed thoſe fiue loaues to the fiue thouſand me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the bread was miraculouſly multiplied, to no leſſe than twelue baſkets full, <hi>Iohn 6.</hi> So when be breake our bread vnto the néedie, God doth as it were by a miracle multiplie the ſame, that in our baſket and in our ſtore, we may neuer want. When the widow of <hi>Sarepta</hi> made the Prophet a little cake with all her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, for this ſhe was the richer, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the barrell of meale waſted not, and the oile in the cruſe ceaſed not, <hi>1. reg. 17.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1847:41"/> 16.</hi> when one <hi>Bonifacius</hi> gaue all his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers corne vnto the poore, for this ſhée was the richer, for behold he praied and the Lord reſtored it in greater abundance than before, <hi>Greg. <hi>li.</hi> 1. <hi>dialog. ca</hi> 9.</hi> When <hi>Iohn</hi> the Patriarke of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> gaue fiue crownes vnto the poore, for this hée was the richer: for behold, a noble Ladie for theſe fiue gaue him fiftie crownes to the vſe of his church, as <hi>Surius</hi> writeth in his life: <hi>Qui enim terrena ſubſidia largitur, ditior dando caeleſti remuneratione redditur,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Hierome</hi> on the <hi>Prouerbs:</hi> Hée that is made poore by giuing his almes, God makes him rich againe by reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his almes. He that thus ſcattereth is the more increaſed, <hi>Prou. 11.29.</hi> Would you then beloued learne the heauenly thrift, loe héere it is, beſtow your treaſure vpon the poore, and it ſhall bring you more profit then gold, <hi>Eccleſ. 29.11.</hi> Would you know where to finde much treaſure, loe héere it is, a mans almes is a purſe with him, and it ſhall pay euerie man his reward vpon his head, as it is in the <hi>13.</hi> verſe of the ſame chap. Would you liue in plentie all the daies of your life, lo
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1847:41"/> héere it is, he that giueth vnto the poore ſhall neuer lacke, <hi>Prou. 28.27.</hi> Would you be aſſured of the reward of your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, loe héere it is, <hi>Caſt your bread vpon the waters, and after manie daies you ſhall finde it.</hi> God is the ſame God ſtill as able to requite, and as ready to reward the déeds of mercy as euer he was: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the bowels of thy charitie ſhall bée ſo farre inlarged, that thou <hi>caſt</hi> all vnto the poore, and leaue nothing for thy ſelfe, yet be thou comforted with that which <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperour ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted himſelfe withall, who hauing ſpent almoſt his whole treaſury in the works of charitie, and being blamed by ſome of his friends for the ſame, returned them this anſwer: Though my money be gone, yet héere is my comfort, <hi>Deus non deerit fiſco noſtro,</hi> God will neuer be wanting in my exchequer: which afterwards he found true: for he did not ſo liberally giue to the poore, as God did liberally reward him with temporall bleſſings for the ſame, as <hi>Paulus Diaconus</hi> in his <hi>3. <hi>libr.</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>6. <hi>cap.</hi>
                  </hi> of his Hiſtorie reporteth.</p>
               <p>Hearken to this O all yée couetous
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1847:42"/> vſurers and extortioners, you that beate your braines and buſie your heads how you may make the greateſt gaine and commoditie of your gold and ſiluer, ſhall I here teach you a new kind of vſury, a more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious courſe, which I thinke you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet heard of, or hearing it, I preſume you neuer yet put in practiſe. If I ſhould ſay vnto you as our Sauiour did to the rich man in the Goſpell, Sell all that you haue and giue to the poore, and you ſhall haue a great reward in heauen; ſurely you would then ſaie, <hi>Durus eſt hic ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> this is a hard ſaying, and with that rich man, you would not abide it. But yet let mée tell you, if you will purchaſe the greateſt gaine by your riches, if you will ſet out your money to vſurie for the beſt commoditie, <hi>caſt,</hi> if not all, yet the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities of your abundance vnto the née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and I will aſſure you by this meanes your gold ſhal bring you greater increaſe, than by all other kinds of vſury whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer: for you know the world is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in ſetting your money to vſury; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you are deceaued by a couſening Lawyer, and hée will teach your debtor a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1847:42"/> tricke to make your bond of none effect: Sometime you are deceaued by a begger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bankabrupt, and where there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as the old ſaying is, not onely the ſubiect but euen the king muſt loſe his right: and ſuppoſe the beſt, that both your debtor and his bond ſtand good, yet the moſt that you get by this meanes, is ſome ten in the hundred, or I will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe twentie, and that peraduenture with ſuch a perplexed conſcience, as if all the furies in hell were already tormenting of you: But in this vſury which I propoſe, behold euery thing ſafe and certaine, <hi>Qui dat pauperi foeneratur domino,</hi> he that giueth vnto the poore ſets out his money to vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to God, and he will recompence that which he hath giuen, <hi>Pro. 19.17.</hi> Here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, your debtor is a ſure pay-maſter, almightie God: the bond or obligation wherewith he tieth himſelfe vnto you, is his word, the leaſt iot and tittle whereof ſhall neuer paſſe: the vſe which he giueth, is not ten in the hundred, but more than ten times beyond the principall, manie temporall bleſſings in this world, which if it be too little, behold a greater reward,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1847:43"/> (which now commeth to be toucht in the laſt place) euerlaſting happineſſe in the world to come; &amp; he that <hi>caſteth his bread vpon the waters ſhall be ſure to find it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt find it.]</hi> That is, thou ſhalt alſo finde this eternall reward. To <hi>caſt our bread vpon the waters.</hi> To giue our almes vnto the poore, ſaith <hi>S. Chryſoſt. <hi>ad pop. Antioch.</hi>
                  </hi> is, <hi>ars omnium quaeſtuoſiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> the moſt gainfull arte of all other; for that is true of this kind of piety which <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of godlineſſe in generall, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all things, hauing the promiſe of this life, and of that which is to come, <hi>1. Tim. 4.8.</hi> It is <hi>Viaticum in mundo, &amp; theſaurus in coelo,</hi> inſtéed of our iourneying prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while we are wandring in this pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of our mortalitie, &amp; a neuer failing treaſure reſerued in heauen for vs: Of the firſt you haue already heard; of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond how ſhould you heare any thing, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fleſh and bloud is able to ſpeake ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of little or nothing, it is too déepe a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be ſounded, too intricate a point to be ſearched, too great a matter to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the ſhallow conceit of a mortall
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1847:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> man; had the <hi>Cherubin</hi> ſanctified my lips as he did the Prophet <hi>Eſ. 6.7.</hi> had I the toong of men and angels, I were not able to expreſſe it: Let vs ſuppoſe all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and delights in this world com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in one, all the glorious ſhewes the eie hath ſéene, all the heauenly ſounds the eare hath heard, all the pleaſant odors the noſe hath ſmelt, al the variety of ſwéet and mellifluous ſauors the toong hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, all the delightfull obiects the hands haue touched: Adde héereunto, not onely what nature, but whatſoeuer arte in her déepeſt knowledge can inuent, and al ſhall be nothing, but as a ſhadow in reſpect of that ſubſtance, as droſſe in reſpect of that gold, as a cottage in reſpect of that pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, as toies and trifles in reſpect of that heauenly reward, which theſe Amners of the Almightie God ſhall receaue in that daie. Then they that haue fedde the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, and clothed the naked in this life, ſhall be made to ſit downe at a table, and Chriſt himſelfe ſhall come foorth and ſerue them: their meat ſhall be of the trée of life, in the midſt of the paradiſe of God: their drinke ſhall be of the water of life, euer
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1847:44"/> flowing and neuer waſting, their appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell ſhall be white arraie, their light ſhall be Chriſt himſelfe, their companions ſhal be angels and archangels, their continual exerciſe ſhall be ſinging and ſaying, Holy, holy, holy, Lord God of hoſts, which was, which is, and which is to come. Héere is that euerlaſting reward of the louers of the poore: thus ſhall it be done to them in heauen, who haue pitied the néedy here on earth. O what a forcible argument ſhould this be to euery one of vs, now with a liberall hand to <hi>caſt our bread vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe waters,</hi> ſéeing at the laſt we ſhall be ſo reſpected, ſéeing at the laſt we ſhall be ſo honored, ſéeing at the laſt wée ſhall finde ſo great and ſo glorious a reward! O what a cooling card will this be to thée, O thou hard hearted worldling, when thou ſhalt ſée the liberall giuer rewarded with heauen, and thy ſelfe thruſt downe to hell! for how wilt thou anſwer the Lord one for a thouſand, when thou canſt not giue account to the Lord of one part in a thouſand, that thou haſt giuen vnto the poore: How wilt thou anſwer him, when it ſhall be told thée, that thou waſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1847:44"/> but Gods ſteward of all that thou didſt poſſeſſe, and therfore thou muſt make an account vnto him, how thou haſt laid out all thy wealth and ſubſtance? What a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable taking wilt thou be in, when thou canſt not but confeſſe that thou haſt ſpent thus much money on thy belly in daintie fare, and thus much money on thy backe in gaie apparell, and thus much money in vanitie, and thus much money in vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie, and thus much money in the ſinne of wantonneſſe, and thus much money in other wickedneſſe, and peraduenture ſcarce one pennie in the works of mercy? Nay what a miſerable taking wilt thou bée in, when thou canſt not but confeſſe that thou hadſt ſo many thouſand pounds abroad at vſurie, and ſo many thouſand pounds at home ruſting in thy treaſurie, and yet in thy life didſt neuer beſtow one pound in the déedes of charitie? Let ſuch rich and wretched men howle and wéepe, for the miſeries that ſhal come vpon them: their riches are corrupt, their garments are moth-eaten, their gold and ſiluer is cankred, and the ruſt thereof ſhall bée a witneſſe againſt them at the laſt day:
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1847:45"/> Eaſier ſhall it bée for a camell to goe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the eie of a néedle, then for ſuch to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdome of heauen. And therefore let all ſuch bunchbackt camels know, if they will be ſaued, they muſt caſt away their burdens that hinder their courſe to this goale, they muſt pare away their bunches that hinder their paſſage through this ſtrait and narrow gate: they muſt diſtribute their goods that otherwiſe will for euer barre them from their God. But to leaue them, and the torments vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they repent, that ſhall neuer leaue them, and to conclude with our ſelues: Many of the ancient autors in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings doe make report of a certaine coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey whoſe faſhion was yéerely to chooſe their king, who had for that yéere abſolute authoritie to doe what he liſt, but the yéere being ended, hée was depoſed from his place, and thruſt naked into a remote Iland, there to end his life in hunger and cold, and much want. Whereof one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aduertiſed, thought aforehand to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent this inconuenience, and in that ſhort time of his raigne, he ſent ouer his wealth and treaſure into that Iland, whereinto
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1847:45"/> himſelfe at the yéeres end being thruſt naked and without meanes, he was relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by that which carefully aforehand he had there prouided. Beloued in our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, were we all kings and princes neuer ſo noble, neuer ſo mightie, neuer ſo rich, we haue no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of any long continuance in this world, no not ſo much as for one yéere: for héere we haue no abiding citie, but we looke for one to come, <hi>Hebr. 13.14.</hi> our yere, that is, our ſhort courſe of life, at laſt muſt haue an end: and as we came naked into the world, ſo muſt we returne naked out of the world, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Iob 1.21.</hi> Let vs then my brethren with that wiſe king now in the time of plenty prouide againſt the future famine let vs now make vs friends of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous mammon, that when we want, they may receiue vs into euerlaſting ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations: let vs now make vs bags that waxe not old, a treaſure that can neuer fail in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: let vs now ſend away wealth in diſtributing to the poore, <hi>Quod enim paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri damus ante nos praemittimus,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Aug. <hi>&amp; hoc ibi inueniemus quod hic damus.</hi>
                  </hi> And
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1847:46"/> we ſhall finde that in heauen which wée giue them héere on earth. Let vs now play the wiſe merchants, as they venture much vpon the waters, ſo let vs vpon <hi>theſe waters. <hi>Regnum coeloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venale eſt,</hi>
                  </hi> this day the kingdome of God is as it were ſet at ſale vnto vs; O let vs ſell all that we haue to buy this pearle: &amp; yet we néed not ſell all, for a ſmall matter will buie it, an ouer-worne garment will buie it, a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of meat will buie it, a loafe of bread will buie it, a draught of drinke will buie it, a cup of cold water will buie it, a mite of ſiluer will buie it; not in reſpect of the merit of ſo ſmall a gift, but in regard of the mercy of ſo great a God: for the word of God muſt bée true when euery man ſhall bée a liar: they that féed the poore when they are hungry, and refreſh them when they are thirſtie, and lodge them when they are wearie, and cloath them when they are naked, and viſite them when they are ſicke, ſhall then be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a <hi>Come yee bleſſed,</hi> inherite an euerlaſting kingdome. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe, they that haue hardned their hearts, &amp; ſhut vp the bowels of compaſſion againſt them,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1847:46"/> ſhall receaue that dolefull ſentence; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part yée curſed into euerlaſting fire, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the diuel &amp; his angels, <hi>Matth. 25.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore (right Honorable, &amp;c.) to conclude all at the laſt: as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I cal heauen and earth to record this day, that I haue ſet before you life and death, bleſſing and curſing, therefore chooſe life, that both thou and thy ſéed may liue, <hi>Deut. 30.19.</hi> So our wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are both in heauen and earth, that this day both life and death are ſet before vs, the euerlaſting reward which God hath prouided for the chearfull giuer, and the heauy iudgement which he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared forthe couetous worldling. O then let vs follow the preſident of the one, and hate the practiſe of the other, that ſo wée may hope for comfort, that ſo we may liue for euer: let vs now admit the poore to our preſence, that then we may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the preſence of God: let vs now giue them our earthly mammon, that then God may giue vs heauenly manna: let vs now receaue them to our table, that then we may be receaued to eate &amp; drinke in the kingdome of God: let vs now make
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1847:47"/> them our companions in earth, that then we may be made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions with angels &amp; archangels in heauen. Let vs now helpe to ſuſtaine their life in this pilgrimage of man, that then we may liue for euer in the citie of God: let vs now crowne them with our temporal bleſſings, that then we may be crowned with the crown of glory: let vs now cloath them with our apparel, that then we may be clothed with the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of immortalitie: let vs now ſhew mercy vnto poore Ieſus in them, that then our Ieſus the God of mercy, may haue compaſſion vpon vs. Finally, let vs now <hi>caſt our bread vpon theſe many and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and ſalt, and running waters</hi> in this world, that then we may find bread and water, the bread of life &amp; the water of life, the riches of Gods treaſurie, &amp; the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his houſe in the world to come. Which the Lord of his infinite mercy grant vnto vs all to enioy after the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of this wofull and wretched life: not for our owne merits and deſerts, but for the moſt glorious paſſion and ioyfull reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt: to whom with the Father, and the bleſſed ſpirit be aſcribed al honor and glory, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1847:47"/>
            <head>The Author to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing ouer intreated at this time to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this Sermon, and hauing my ſelfe ſo manie neceſſarie imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments otherwiſe, I was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſend vnto the Printer, that one and only vnperfect co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py which I had thereof; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if (by reaſon of mine owne abſence) there happen to be many faults, the Chriſtian and
<pb facs="tcp:1847:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> well diſpoſed Reader, I hope, wil charitably cenſure them. As for the carping companions of our time, as I neuer deſired to pleaſe them, ſo doe I not now ſeeke to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1847:48"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
